...
With these new data types in mind,
strings, with some of the other pieces we've added in,
let's go back and just remind ourselves
about branching programs so that we can build on that to start
creating iterative programs.
So just to remind you, what's a branching program?
It's something where I have a conditional that I test.
If that test returns the Boolean value true,
then I have a block of code I'm going to run.
If it returns the Boolean value false,
I've got something different I'm going to run.
And I'm going to simply take either this branch
or that branch and pick up the remainder of the code.
We've already seen a simple version of that with an IF.
To do the testing, we had comparisons,
things like comparisons on ints and floats.
These are simple numerical things.
I will simply remind you again the double equal checks
equality, equal sign does not.
And we had logical operations to put things together.
With that in mind, we could start then
building the simplest of the branching code, which
were either IF statements, which says if this condition is true,
execute a set of code.
And IF ELSE, which said if this condition is true do this,
otherwise do that.
Or the more general, IF ELIF ELSE,
which says if this condition is true, do this.
If it's false, check to see if this condition is true,
in which case do this.
And keep doing that until I get through all of the ELIF
clauses, and if all of the conditions are false,
pick up the ELSE clause and do the rest of that.
It's just repeating what we've done before, things
that you've already seen.
With that though, I'm still stuck
with things that can only flow through code once.
I can take different branches to get there,
but I can't go back and do something again.
And let's think about where that might actually not
help the way I'd like.
As I said, simple branching programs just make choices.
Sometimes though I might want to do something
over and over and over again.
How would I do that?
Well, imagine you're writing a simple little video game.
And part of that game has a character
that gets lost in some woods.
And I agree the graphics here aren't great,
but you get the idea.
I'm stuck in a set of woods.
What I'd like to do is to say to the character, if you go right,
you're going to get back to the same place.
You're going to be stuck in the same piece of the woods.
How would I write that as code?
Well, you could say, gee, I could have an IF statement that
says if I'm told to go right, here's
a set of things I want to do, otherwise if I go left,
I'll get out of there.
OK?
But I want this to be something that if I keep going right,
I keep getting stuck in the same spot.
All right.
You say, gee, that's easy.
I could have another IF statement
that says if the command is still exit right, do something.
On the other hand, if I exit left,
I'll get out of the woods.
But I didn't want to do that again.
If I'm going right, I want to keep doing it.
You can see the problem.
I want to be in literally an infinite loop
in this little video game that says if I'm going right,
I'm always coming back to the same spot.
How would I write code to do that?
Well, I could say I'm going to assume that a character doesn't
push go right more than 100 times,
and I could write literally a big loop here-- not a loop,
sorry-- a big sequence of IFs that was 100 deep.
But maybe somebody is really persistent,
and they want to do it 1,000 times.
You could see my problem.
I don't want to write code when I have an indeterminate number
of things that I want to do.
I need a different way of controlling this,
and I have that.
It's called a while loop.
We're going to look at it in detail,
but the idea is that I'm going to say here's
a check, a condition.
If it's true, I'm going to do this,
and I'm going to go back around and do it again.
And I'll keep looping around and around on this while
until this condition is false, in which case
I'll jump out and do the next kind of thing.
And that says, no matter how many times I go right,
I'll always be in that loop until I finally go left
and break out of it.
So I can control the flow.
Now, for the first time, not just
in a linear way with something that lets me check conditions.
And so the format of a while loop is very simple.
There's the while expression.
There's a test that's going to return a Boolean value,
either true or false, and then with indentation
a set of expressions I'm going to evaluate.
And the performance of this is exactly what I just described.
If the condition is true, I'm going
to do all the steps inside that code block.
I'm going to go back up and check the condition.
And I'll keep going through that loop
until the condition finally comes out as false.
All right.
How might I use that to do something a little more
interesting than trying to get out of the woods?
Well, first of all, let's fix the woods.
Here's a nice little piece of code that will do that for me.
The first one says input based on this prompt,
an instruction, left or right.
So n's going to be either the word left or the word right.
Notice what the while loop says.
It says, if n is equal to the string right,
then I'm going to execute this block of code,
which simply again says you're in the lost forest.
Go left to right.
And notice what that while loop will now do.
As long as n is equal to right, it
will keep prompting me, asking for an input, until I
finally type in left, at which case, this will be false,
and I'll jump down and pick up the print statement.
I can have an indeterminate number of times here.
It's still always going to do the same thing.
A little brain damaged, but it's still
going to do the right thing.
And that's kind of nice.
Now, let's see how we might use this then
in other kinds of things.
So here's a while loop.
And notice what I need to do inside a while loop.
I need to set up a variable outside so that I can test it
and then do some pieces.
And I need inside to have something that actually changes
that variable, otherwise I'm never
going to get out of the loop.
Now, we can see what this does.
If I type this into my Python shell,
I can set n equal to 0, which is done.
And then I can say while n is less than 5 colon,
I'm going to print out n, and I'm going to set n to n plus 1.
Cool.
It just did what I'd expected.
It starts out with n equal to 0.
Is 0 less than 5?
You bet.
So it prints out n, changes n by 1, goes back around
and checks again.
Is 1 less than 5?
You bet.
And you get the idea.
That pattern is something that we would use pretty regularly.
That pattern is also slightly annoying,
because what if I forget to set n equal to 0 before I start?
I'm either going to get an error, because n isn't bound
to anything, or I'm going to get a performance I don't expect,
because n has got some value I didn't expect.
Similarly, what if I forget to increment?
I set n equal to 0, and I say while n is less than 5,
print n.
Well, I'm going to print out 0 a billion times
until I finally stop the machine,
because I haven't incremented.
So it turns out there's another form that we're
going to use that is much more convenient,
and that's called a for loop.
And the for loop has a particular syntax.
It has a variable.
It has the key word in in this case,
and then it has something we're going to come back to
in a second, but an expression.
And what for does in this case is
it is going to work through all of the values
returned by that expression one at a time,
executing the body of the code.
Now, range is something that returns
basically a sequence of integers starting at 0
and ending before 5.
0, 1, 2 3, 4.
It actually does something a little different
we're going to talk about later in the course,
but think of it for now as giving us the collection
of integers 0 up through 4.
And so if I go over here and type it,
I say for n in range of 0 to 5, print out n.
I get the same behavior, but this code is easier to see.
It says for n in this sequence, do something.
As we said, range gives us back, in essence, the integers
0 up through 4.
We'll see some other variations on range
shortly in terms of other ways in which we control it.
But the for loop gives us a nice way
to capture easily an iteration, a repeating of code
some number of times based on, in this case,
a specific number, although I could also base it on a test.
Just to recapture this then, the overall general
format for a for.
The special character in, in this case using
range to get me out a set of numbers and a body of code
that I'm going to execute.
And just to remind you again it says,
each time through the loop, variable
is going to take a value.
The first time it starts at the smallest value in range.
The next time it gets the next value, in this case, for range
added by 1 and so on.
Now, I can actually be a little more clever about range,
because maybe I don't want to do every value in that range.
Maybe I want to skip some of them.
So, in fact, I have something that
says I can start at a different point than 0
if I give it two arguments.
In this case, it will give me the range of numbers from 7
up to but not including 10, or I can give it three arguments.
Start at 5, end when I get up to or past 11, but do it by 2.
And in each case, I'm going to get a different range out.
So let's look at what those do.
If I go over here and say my sum is 0,
and then I'm going to say for i in the range 7 to 10,
I'm going to increment my sum by i.
And then if I print out my sum, I
get 7, 8, and 9 added together, which
gives me out the thing I would expect to see.
If I do the second one, my sum again
starts out as 0, and for i in the range 5 to 11 by 2,
this should be 5, 7, 9, but not 11.
And, again, I'm going to say my sum I'm
going to increment by i, and remember plus equal says
add to my sum the value of i.
And I print out my sum.
I get 21 in this case-- 5 plus 7 plus 9.
Sounds right.
So I can use range to actually give me a set of values,
but the nice part about all of this is the for loop
always will just run through all of those values
and executing the body of the loop each time through.
Now, as I'm doing these loops, it
might be the case that I want to get out of one of them.
I might want to stop if something is actually,
for example, a condition is true.
And for that, I have another special thing called a break
and does exactly what you would expect.
If I'm running through some code,
and I execute or see rather that special key word break,
it stops the execution of that loop at that point or that code
block at that point and breaks out of it.
So in this case, if I'm inside this while
loop, when I hit break, it will never execute that expression.
It will pop out of all of this and pick up at that point.
That lets me control how I want to deal with loops.
For example, I might see a particular condition is true
and, based on that, say I don't want to do the rest of this
and jump out of it.
I could write it as an if, but the break
gives me a natural way to control
where I am inside of that loop.
And so there's an example.
I could set my sum equal to 0.
I could run over that range, but I'd say in this case
if it's actually equal to 5, I can just break out.
While I'm typing that in, think about what this might do.
So I'm going to set my sum to 0, for i in range 5 to 11 by 2.
I'm going to increment my sum by i,
and then I'm going to say if my sum is equal to 5, break out.
And what do you think?
If I look at the value of my sum, it's just 5,
which is exactly what I'd expect,
because the first time around i is going to have the value 5.
I'm going to increment my sum by 1, but then this test is true,
and this break pulls me out of that entire loop
and stops the computation.
Silly example, I agree, but it lets
you see how break controls the actual processing, breaking
myself out of a loop when I decide I'm ready to do that.
And there's the body of code it's going to break out of,
which is why it stops after only the first stage.
To put all of these together, here's
a little summary of for and while loops.
In a for loop, we know the number
of times it's going to run through an iteration,
although I can end it early with a break.
Because I've defined the range of things over which
I'm going to do the work.
It uses a counter that's captured
inside the for loop itself.
I can always rewrite a for loop as a while loop
by taking that variable that I'm using, that counter I'm using,
pulling it outside, initializing it, and explicitly doing
the increment to the counter inside of the loop.
A while loop can have an unbounded or unknown number
of iterations.
Again, I can always end it early with a break statement,
but I here have to set up the counter ahead
of time outside of the loop.
And I have to make sure I increment it inside the loop.
And unfortunately, I can't always
rewrite a while loop using a for loop.
You'll see in most code, we tend to use for loops
when we know what we're going to do as a computation.
We'll use the while loop when there's
going to be a condition that we can't
predict that's going to allow us to break out of that loop.
But both of them give us the first version
of iterative algorithms.