...
This notion of an iterative algorithm is really valuable.
It broadens dramatically the class
of things that we can compute.
Again, if I just have branching things,
I can only go through the code once.
Now, I can start generalizing.
And so we've got things that do much more
than just the simple arithmetic we were doing earlier.
We can repeat a sequence of steps
multiple times based on the decision.
One of the things that comes out naturally
once we have this idea of repeating things
is a set of methods that are sometimes
called guess-and-check methods.
They're very useful, even though they're not always
the most efficient technique.
And I want to extend that notion of iterative algorithms
to capture examples of guess-and-check methods.
Go back to what we talked about in an earlier lecture.
Remember we had that declarative definition of square root.
Square root of x was that y such that y squared was equal to x.
And I said, if we were lucky, somebody gave us a guess.
We could at least use it to check whether we were right.
Now, we went and looked a different direction.
We looked at an algorithm to actually compute it,
but we can go back to that idea, because if we had a good way
to generate guesses, we could use that declarative definition
to check.
That's the basis of guess-and-check.
I'm going to have to come up with a way of systematically
making guesses for the possible answer,
check them, and keep doing that in an iterative algorithm
until I find a good solution.
Let's see how we might do that.
I'm going to use cube root rather than square root
just to change it up a little bit,
but the same idea would work.
One way to use this idea would be to try and find,
for example, starting at 0, try 0 cubed,
then 1 cubed, then 2 cubed, and so on, until I get to a point
where I find a k such that k cubed is greater than x.
If I found the square root-- sorry,
the cube root before then, I stop,
but once I've got something greater than x,
I know I can stop.
Now, clearly this is only going to work for integers.
I can't do it for all possible numbers.
But in this case there's only a finite number of things
that I need to try.
So let's see what that would do.
Here's some code that would actually make it happen.
I'm going to start by inputting an integer.
Notice my use of input.
I'll remind you that says it's going to print out
that message, then read in whatever I type
in into the environment inside Python.
Remember that input returns something as a string,
so I'm going to convert it into an integer.
It's going to assume I typed in an integer.
If I give it something else, it's not going to work.
And then I'm just going to have a little loop.
I'm going to set up answer to be 0,
and then as long as I have something that's
less than the thing I'm trying to find the cube of,
I'm just going to increment-- add 1 to it.
And I'm going to keep doing that until I get something that
is equal to-- sorry, something where the cube is either
equal to x or greater than x.
And once I get there, I'll simply check to see,
did I actually get the cube, by doing a test.
Let's try this out.
Again, I've got a little piece-- same piece of code over here.
I'm going to load it into my system.
It says "enter an integer."
Let's give it something reasonable, like 27.
So in my environment, I give it 27.
Ah, good.
Cube root is in fact 3.
Let's try something else.
Again, I'm going to load this into my system,
and I don't know, let's pick 38.
And it says, doesn't work.
It's not a perfect cube.
All right.
My code runs.
What was this doing?
It's simply using a loop, right here, to generate guesses.
And it's going to keep doing that until it gets
either to something that is the right thing,
or has gone too far, in which case,
I'm simply going to do a check to see which case I'm in.
Here, I'm using that declarative knowledge,
because there's the test.
Test is right there to see, do I have something
that is in fact the cube root?
That's nice.
That's what I'd like.
What could I say about this piece of code?
Well, first of all, it's only going
to work for positive integers.
OK.
I could easily fix that by just keeping track of the sign
and then [INAUDIBLE] the solution to the positive case.
And I do this because one of the things we want to do with code
is think about how well does it run?
Does it run on all the things I expected?
And how might I modify it?
And here the modification is actually
pretty straightforward.
I'm going to do the same kind of thing.
I'm going to run the code, but I'm
going to use "abs," which is a built in function,
to take the absolute value of x.
I'm going to check the cube root against the absolute value
of x.
And then when I'm done, I can just decide down here
whether in fact I want the negative or positive version
of that.
I could make that change and run it.
I'm not going to do it.
It'll work for me, but it simply shows you
that I can easily extend my code to build new versions of things
to handle cases that I didn't think about when I wrote
the first version of the code.
There's the first version of a guess-and-check method.
A little slow, but it does the right kind of thing.
Now, one of the things that we've talked about
is that we know when we do a loop that we
need some characteristics.
In particular, we need a loop variable
that's initialized outside the loop, that
changes within the loop, and that's
used to test when I'm done.
That notion we can also capture in a little bit
more general form, because it's useful to think about what's
happening inside the loop.
How do I know the loop's actually going to stop?
And for that, we often want to think
about something we call a decrementing function.
The idea is that we're going to map all of the program
variables into an integer, and when the loop is entered,
that value is going to be something that's non-negative.
When I go through the loop, it's going to keep decreasing,
and when that value gets less than or equal to 0,
I know I want to terminate.
So this is a capturing of this idea of the loop variable
in terms of looking at what's being done inside the loop.
And in my case here, I was simply
using the absolute value of x minus answer cubed
as my decrementing function.
If you think about it, every time through the loop,
that is decreasing.
And once it gets to a stage where
it's either less than or equal to 0, I'm ready to stop,
and I'm going to be able to go on
to see whether I've actually computed-- sorry,
a perfect cube or not.
What could go wrong?
Well, these are the standard problems with a loop.
Suppose I don't initialize the variable.
Most likely thing is I get something called a name
error, which is I'm going to try and refer
inside the loop to something that I haven't defined
outside the loop.
There is no value.
I can't look it up.
That's at least OK.
I'm going to stop.
What's worse is if I've used that loop variable somewhere
else in my code before this, I'm actually
going to get something that starts off
the computation in a place I don't expect,
and that's a harder problem to find.
So this is one of the things we always
want to remember with loops-- make
sure we initialize the variable before we start it.
What if I forget to change the variable inside the loop?
I'm in trouble, because I'm going to go through that loop
until I get really tired of the machine running.
It's going to simply go through what we call an infinite loop,
doing exactly the same code over and over and over again,
because it will never reach a terminating condition.
And those are two standard problems with using a loop.
A while-loop, in particular, is I've
gotta make sure I set up the variable ahead of time.
I've gotta make sure I'm changing it inside the loop.
And I need to make sure that the termination test is actually
using that variable appropriately.
But as long as I get into the discipline of that
set the variable, write the loop,
decrement the variable inside the loop, and check for it,
I should be OK.
So that gives us actually a broad class of algorithms.
Not the most efficient, not going to work in every case,
but a good guess-and-check algorithm
is something where you guess a value,
you check to see if it's right, you change the conditions
inside the loop, and you keep guessing
until you find a solution or you've used up
all the possible values.
This is an example of a set of algorithms
called exhaustive enumeration, and you
can see why "exhaustive."
Two reasons.
One, you're going to exhaust all possible options to use.
And two is it's going to take a while to run,
so you get tired waiting for it to finish.
But as computers get faster, surprisingly,
many of these algorithms can actually work quite well.
On the other hand, I might not want
to always think about making sure I initialize a loop
variable, do a while-loop and then change it inside.
So I could clean this code up by using
the other kind of variable-- sorry,
the other kind of iteration structure, a for-loop.
So here's a nice variation of that.
I could set up a value for cube.
I could have read it in, but I could set up
a value for the thing I'm trying to find the cube
root of, and then just run a for-loop, because I know
that the cube root has to be less than cube itself,
at least for positive integers, things greater than 1.
So I can simply use "range" to generate all possible things
I want to use as a guess, and then
run a for-loop, where I'll run this and simply say, again,
check to see, is guess cube equal to cube?
If it is, I'm done.
Let's see what happens if we find-- if we try that one out.
So I've got a little simple version of that over here.
I'm going to start off with cube equal to 8.
And if I run it, does the right thing.
It says cube root of 8 is 2.
Let's try 27.
And if I run that, wow, it's great.
Cube root of 27 is 3.
This is working really well.
OK.
But suppose I now give it something different, like 28,
and I run it.
Hm.
What happened?
Well, it completed.
I can check that over here, if I go back to my process.
I've got things here, but it didn't print anything out.
Ah, because I made a slip when I wrote the code.
That code is going to run through all possible options
for guess, but it's only going to print something out
if in fact I find something that is the cube root-- if there
is a perfect cube.
28, that's not going to happen.
It didn't give me anything informative.
So I ought to clean that up, and I can, by simply saying,
do the same thing.
I've actually cleaned it up to add
an "abs" here so that I'm going to deal
with the negative cases.
But do the check here, and if I get to a place
where I've gone too far, simply break.
Break out of it.
OK?
Otherwise, run through the loop, but now, when I do the check,
do the print.
Otherwise, do the check with the second piece.
And actually, I've done that in an inverse way.
Here I'm checking to see it's not a perfect cube,
and I'm going to print that out.
If it is a perfect cube, I'm going
to basically determine whether I want the positive or negative
version of it.
So I'm cleaning up two things here.
I'm allowing for negative integers,
but I'm also allowing for it to print out something that's
going to do the right thing.
And let me show you what would happen if I run that version.
So now when I run this, cube root of minus 27 is minus 3.
And if I give it a minus 28, it says it's not a perfect cube.
And I'm all set.
What was my point?
When I run the code, I shouldn't just
run it on things I'm expecting, like perfect cubes.
I should run it on other things to see
if it does the right thing.
When it didn't, I wanted to add in a different check,
and I added in a second thing here which
I had done earlier, which is to make
sure I can deal with negative integers and not just positive
integers.
But that now gives us a nice tool.
I've got exhaustive enumeration, guess-and-check methods that
can work on problems where there's
a finite number of choices.
I can come up with a way of exhaustively testing
all of those, and it's a good way
to generate guesses in an organized manner using
those iterative loops as a technique to tell when I'm done
and to return a great answer.
And we're going to build on that idea as we move on.