...
Now that we have the idea that we want to put together
expressions, by putting together primitives in legal ways,
we can take up that idea of how to use
that to start capturing recipes, start capturing algorithms.
So let's talk about a Python program.
Python being the language we're going
to use in this class to do programming.
And the program, just as you saw with the recipe,
is going to be a sequence of definitions and commands.
Definitions as we'll see a little bit later on,
are ways of either assigning names to values,
or more importantly, creating procedures
that we're going to treat as if they're primitives.
Those we refer to as being evaluated.
Commands, are simpler expressions
that we can execute directly within Python.
And we do that in something called a shell.
In a moment I'm going to use a shell.
A shell is simply a window into which I can type expressions.
They get passed into the Python interpreter,
it follows the set of instructions to figure out
what's the semantics -- what's the meaning associated with
that expression?
And then it prints out the result.
Commands are statements that instruct the interpreter to do
something.
So the commands could be simply, do this arithmetic operation.
Or commands could be apply a primitive that I
created to do some work for us.
The last piece, and we're going to see both of these
as we go through the course, is that we can either type things
directly into the shell.
That's a window that the interpreter is listening to.
That's something where we type something in
and the machine does something with it.
Or, we can store it in a file that gets read into the shell
when we're ready to use it.
But otherwise, can be saved away.
To start with, we're just gonna type directly into the shell,
but we'll see examples of files in a little bit.
OK, we're almost ready to start programming.
We know the pieces we need.
Let's start with what are the fundamental primitives that
represent data?
Those, we call objects.
And programs manipulate data objects
in order to get out parts of those objects
or to do something with those objects.
Every object has a type associated with it
that tells us what kind of thing it is.
And more importantly, that type is really important.
That type tells programs whether they can act on it or not.
If a program is expecting a number and I give it a string,
it's not going to try and do something with it.
So the type of the object is really valuable.
Finally, objects come either as scalars, which
says they can't be subdivided.
Or, if they're scalars, obviously
non-scalars which are things that
have internal structure into which we can pull out parts.
Let's start with the simplest version of these,
scalar objects in Python.
There are very few of them.
We have ints.
These are integers.
Standard numbers that you recognize, 5.
17.
27.
Minus 6.
We have floats.
These are real numbers, things with numbers
after the decimal point.
3.27.
3.14159, my favorite.
You have something called a bool, short for Boolean.
And that represents true or false.
Those are going to be important when
we get to tests, because we want to know if a test is true,
do something.
If it's not, do something else.
There's one weird one.
It's called NoneType.
It's a very special one.
It has only one value, which is none.
We're going to see why that's important later on,
but just to be careful, NoneType is a scalar object.
Those are four fundamental scalars.
There are only a couple of more, which we'll get to a little
later on.
Once I have knowledge of those different types,
I can also find out the type of an object,
by using a built-in procedure called type.
And I want to show you some examples.
So I'm going to go over to my little machine over here,
and I'm going to skip down.
I'm now talking to a shell.
And you'll notice it's got a little prompt that says in,
saying what's the input you want to give?
The fact it's got 30 on the machine
is because I was doing some other work earlier.
So this is going to be the 30th expression typed in.
And I'm simply going to type in a number.
And the output is the number itself.
Well duh, you say.
But it's actually important, because what the machine did
was it read in that sequence of characters, understood
that it was a number, and the value
associated with the number is simply the number.
And in fact, I can check it because I
can say what's the type of 3.5?
Notice the open and close parentheses around it.
And it says, it's a float.
And I can have integers.
And if I say what's the type of that,
it's going to give me back an int.
Simple things.
OK.
Again, just to recap what this says is here's
what I'm going to type into this Python shell.
And here's what shows up after I hit Enter as you just saw.
And in and out are simply going to identify what I typed in,
in the output that you've recovered.
Sometimes I want to change types, especially with numbers.
This is called casting.
And I can cast types of different forms,
and you can see the example.
If I say, I want to take an int, such as 5,
and turn it into a float I can ask it to do so, by giving it
the special command float -- the thing contained within
parentheses -- and it converts it.
The other direction also works.
If I want to take a float, such as 3.9,
and convert it into an int.
Here you say, boy there might be some choices.
Python simply gives the whole number part of it.
It doesn't round it to the nearest integer,
as you might expect.
If you want to build your own programming language,
knock yourself out.
You could do that.
But it simply will truncate it down to that int.
So I can convert back and forth.
Now, once I've got these things, I
can start putting things together.
And in particular, here's a legal expression.
3 plus 2.
That has a value associated with it.
In fact, that expression is to take the 3 and the 2
and apply the arithmetic operation of addition to them.
And when I evaluate it, it simply returns out 5.
Makes sense.
Sometimes I might want to use something
that's going to print.
And I can type, for example, print
which controls output to the console
by saying print 3 plus 2.
Huh.
Little bit of a difference.
And in fact, there's no out here because no value is returned.
Print returns that NoneType and doesn't print anything out.
It just printed something.
At this stage, you may be saying, well why do this?
Why the difference?
What we're going to see is, when we're
in the middle of a computation and we want to print something
out to the shell, we can use a print command to do that.
If we just return the value, that
goes back into the computation to be used for the next step.
And so in the simple first case, the whole value
of the computation was 3 plus 2 equals 5.
It was printing all 5.
In the second case, the side effect is to print something.
The value returned is nothing.
There is no value.
We'll come back to that as we go along.
I've already hinted at this, but now we
can start putting things together.
To combine objects and operators into expressions,
we use a standard form.
And the syntax is simply an object, an operator,
and another object.
Any expression like this that is syntactically valid,
has a value, which is itself a type.
So we talk about the types of scalar objects,
we talk about the types of more complicated expressions.
What would those expressions look like?
Well, here's the first set of them.
There's a lot on this slide, but you're
going to get used to them.
And most of them make sense.
If I want to add together either two ints or two floats,
my expression is to have two numbers
as I just did, 3 plus 2.
The value associated with that is the combination
of adding the two things together.
I can subtract, I can multiply.
And for these examples, if both I and J are ints,
the result is an int.
If either of them or both of them are floats,
the result is a float.
And let's look at an example.
If I do 3 plus 2, I get 5.
If I do 3.0 plus 2, I get the float 5.
So Python is always using, if you like,
the higher level representation when it
does those kinds of operations.
Divisions, a little trickier, because I
have both standard division, which will be a float,
and I have integer division, which
will be the quotient without the remainder.
And let's look at two examples.
If I do 5 divided by 2, I get 2 and 1/2.
If I do 5 with two slashes divided by 2,
I get the integer part, which is 2.
The .5 is thrown away.
And if I wanted to get the .5 I could
do 5 remainder 2, which is the percent sign,
and that gives me the piece left over when I divide those two
pieces together.
Finally, I can raise something to a power.
And that is done right here with I. Two stars, J. So one star
is multiplication.
Two stars, gives me power.
Once I've got that, I'm ready to start putting together pieces.
In particular, I've got different operations.
So I have to think about how do I put together pieces in ways
that control what I want to do?
And here, we're going to use parentheses
to tell Python in what order to do the operations.
There's a precedence to those operations.
And those are shown right down here, going in this order.
Exponentiation, powers are always done first.
Then multiplications, then divisions.
And then finally, additions or subtractions.
And overall it's done in a left to right order, as it
appears inside the expression.
And that means that as I change where the parentheses are,
I'm changing the order in which I'm doing things.
So to do an example, if I take 3 times 5 plus 1.
That's going to give me 16.
And that's because the multiplication is done first,
3 times 5 gives me 15.
And then the addition is done, to give me 16.
On the other hand, if I say 3 times,
and then in parentheses 5 plus 1,
the parentheses say reduce this expression first.
Add 5 and 1.
That gives me 6.
And then do the multiplication, which gives me the 18.
As a consequence.
I can create very complicated expressions.
And I will simply use parens open
and close-- to define what operations to do first.
Always simplifying inside out, before then using the operator
precedence order, in order to decide what
the expression actually means.