...
So far, we've just been playing with numbers-- names
for numbers but basically just with numbers.
Now we want to add in one more type of object.
We've seen ints, we've seen floats,
we've seen bools, which are ways of getting values
back out of tests.
The next thing we're going to add in is a string.
We'll see a few others as we go along,
but strings are going to be valuable to us.
And what's a string?
A string is simply a sequence of characters-- letters,
special characters.
Could be spaces, could actually be sequences
of characters put together into words,
put together into sentences.
And those are all contained within either double quotation
marks or single quotes.
Let me show you some examples.
I've got some on my slide, but let
me show you some examples with my screen.
I can give the name hi to the string H-E-L-L-O space
T-H-E-R-E double quote.
Those quotes on either end say treat this entire sequence
as literally a sequence of characters.
And if I ask for the value of hi,
it prints it back out, in this case,
with a single quote around it.
As we said, we can either use double quotes or single quotes.
Why?
Partly historical.
One would really work, but a place
where double quotes are handy is if I actually
want to use an apostrophe somewhere in a string.
Because from Python's perspective,
the apostrophe looks like an end of a quote.
And so for example, if I want to say foo is this isn't right,
notice that the single quote does not get interpreted
as the end of a quote.
And I can put out the value of foo.
Once I've got strings, I can put them together.
So for example, I could say I'm going
to give name the value Eric.
I could certainly print out name.
What's its value?
There it is.
But I could also put things together.
And the next expression looks a little unusual.
Greet is hi plus name.
And when I print out greet-- sorry, if I type properly,
it would help.
Print out greet.
It puts the two things together-- hi there and Eric.
Two things going on here.
The first one is-- whoa, little funky
to think about adding strings together.
But just as we can add numbers together,
strings have a natural way of getting combined.
And in this case, it's to concatenate them together,
to literally take the first string, glue the second string
onto the end, that creates a new string, and I can print it out.
But if you look at my computer monitor,
it didn't quite do what I wanted.
It said hello Theric.
I have no idea who Theric is.
I'd really like to have it say hello there, Eric.
And so I can get that by adding in a little blank space.
And so if I type in greeting as hi plus a space plus name,
then the value of greeting is what I wanted-- hello there,
Eric.
Really nice.
Notice concatenation, just as with numbers,
could have multiple things in a row.
So I can concatenate multiple things together as I did here.
What we say when we talk about using addition this way,
by the way, is we say we have overloaded it.
We have had addition apply not only to numbers but now
to strings.
Oh, yeah.
We talked about that earlier on.
Remember when I said in the first lecture
that the type of an argument, the type of an object,
would tell an operation some important information?
Here it does that because it's telling addition,
if the two things are strings, concatenate them.
It's also telling addition, if I give you two numbers,
just add them together using straightforward arithmetic.
So I can use addition in multiple places
to let the type of the object define what's going to happen.
Once I have strings, I need operations on them.
I've already seen the first one.
We can do concatenation, but we can do some other things
with strings.
In particular, we can do successive concatenation.
So if I type three times the string Eric, I get an echo.
Three versions of Eric are stitched together.
So I can successively concatenate things together.
It's kind of nice.
And, again, notice I'm overloading multiplication
here.
I'm saying multiplication of a number times a string is simply
saying give me three versions or n versions,
however many versions of that string put together.
I can ask for the length of a string, and that makes sense.
It tells me how many characters there are in that string.
And that will include, by the way, counting spaces.
So the length of hi there includes the space, not just
the characters.
It tells me how many literal elements there
are inside of it.
Strings have things inside of them.
They're the first version of a non-scalar object,
in that I can get out pieces.
And one of the ways I can do it is say I can index into it.
So if I take the string, Eric, and I
want to get out the first element in square brackets,
I can say give me the first element, and it gives me r.
Wait a minute.
That's not the first element.
The First element's e.
Eh, in Python we have chosen to decide to start
counting starting at 0.
So if I want to get the zeroth element of Eric,
I would say give me the zeroth element, and there it is.
I've already bound name to be Eric so notice, by the way,
I could ask for the zeroth element of name,
and it gives me the zeroth element of the value associated
with name, which pulls back out the e, exactly what I wanted.
If I try and index beyond the length minus 1 of a string,
I'm going to get an error.
And that's because I start at 0.
So even though this is of length 4, if I take the string Eric
and I ask what's the fourth element?
It gives me an error, something called an index error
that says you tried to go too far outside of it.
One last thing about strings.
I can certainly get a single element out.
I might want to get a chunk out of it.
And so I can slice a string apart by giving it a somewhat
funky looking expression.
I take Eric and, again, in those square braces
I give it a starting point, which is 1, and a colon,
and then an ending point, in this case 3,
and it gives me the first and second elements
of the string, r and i.
I can choose to say everything starting at the beginning,
I could use that as a 0, but I can also
do that by saying give Eric with nothing
before the colon and just 3, and it gives me all the elements
up to but not including the element number 3.
And similarly, I could do it by saying take Eric,
give it 1, but nothing after the colon,
and it gives me all the elements starting at element number 1.
And if I just want to make a copy of the whole thing,
I can say open square brace colon close square brace,
and it gives me literally a copy-- not the original--
but a copy of this entire string.