...
We've just seen an example of an algorithm that
computes floating point numbers as an answer,
and we've been playing with floats earlier on.
I now want to take a little sidetrack to talk about floats
and how they're represented inside the computer.
And in particular, to deal with something
that you may have experienced earlier on in the course, where
you'll get answers that will give you
some funny number where you expecting 3.0,
and it gives you 3.00000125 or something else.
To deal with this, we need to go inside the machine for a second
and talk about how floats represent real numbers.
They certainly approximate them, but it's
useful to get a sense of how the machine actually stores it,
because it can't store an infinite number
of decimal points or digits after the decimal point
inside the machine.
Here's the basic idea.
Let's start with a decimal number, the numbers
you're used to dealing with.
The number 302 is really 3 times 10
squared plus 0 times 10 to the first power plus 2 times 10
to the 0-th power or 1.
It's 300 plus zero 10s plus two 1s.
Binary numbers, which is how the computer store things,
are actually represented the same way, but now
in terms of powers of 2.
So the number 10011 in binary is 1 times
2 to the fourth, plus 0 times 2 cubed, plus 0 times 2 squared,
plus 1 times 2 to the 1, plus 1 times 2 to the 0.
Which is actually 16 plus 2 plus 1, or 19 in decimal notation.
Internally, the computer represents
every number in binary, whether it's an integer
or it's a float.
How would we use that idea to think about how do we represent
floating point numbers?
Well, let's think about how we could convert a decimal integer
into a binary representation, and then we'll
do the fraction portion of it.
So given a decimal integer, how would we convert it to binary?
Well, let's take an example.
My example would be the one I just had before.
19 in decimal is 10011 in binary.
If I had 19, or anything that represents that number,
how could I get it out?
Well, what I can do is the following little trick.
I can take the remainder of that number relative to 2,
and that remainder actually gives me the last binary bit.
It'll give me this bit right here,
because that's the remainder that's left when I divide by 2.
If I then take x and divide it by 2 integer-wise using
that double slash idea, all of the bits get shifted right.
That is x double divide by 2 is now 1 times 2 to the third
rather than 2 to the fourth, plus 0 times 2
squared rather than 2 to the third, plus 0 times 2 to the 1
rather than 2 squared, plus 1 times 2
to the zero rather than 2 to the one.
Or another way of saying it, and notice I've taken these digits
and just shifted them to the right.
If I keep doing successive divisions like this,
I can keep track of each of the bits
that comes out, because the remainder gives me
the next bit.
And when I'm done with all of that,
I've converted to binary form.
So basic idea, given an integer, take the remainder with respect
to 2.
That's the low order bit.
Divide integer-wise by 2, shifts right.
Do the same thing until I've exhausted the entire integer
representation.
So here's a little piece of code that would do exactly that.
If the number is less than 0, I'm
going to put on a flag that says it's negative.
And I'm going to use the positive version of it
by taking the absolute value of that number.
Otherwise I'm going to put in a flag that says it's not.
And then I'm going to simply accumulate those results.
If the number is equal to 0, it's just 0.
That's pretty obvious.
Otherwise, as long as the number is greater than 0,
I'm going to do remainder, add that in,
because that's the next bit into result,
do the division to shift it to the right, and keep going.
So if I look at that, here's a simple example
of doing that conversion, converting decimal to binary.
I'll start with a real simple example.
If I start off with number as 3 and I do that computation,
I didn't print anything, but the result is sitting in result.
And there I get it.
The binary representation of 3 is, not surprisingly, 1 plus 2.
Let's just check to make sure I wasn't misleading you
when I said 19 was, in fact, what I claimed it was.
So if I make it 19, and I run it, and I look at result,
it gives me back 10011, exactly as I said.
All right, cool, so I can take integers and convert them
into binary, but I started talking about floats.
So how do I deal with the fraction part of this?
Well, I can do almost the same thing.
Let's take an example.
3/8 is 0.375.
And in binary, that is 3 times 10 to the minus 1 plus 7 times
10 to the minus 2 plus 5 times 10 to the minus 3.
It's just the digits associated with each of the placeholders.
Here's the trick I'm going to play.
If I can find a power of 2 big enough to convert all of that
into a whole number-- that is, multiply it by something so
that it gets converted into a whole number,
then I can convert that into binary.
I just did that, I know how to do that.
And then when I'm done, just divide by that same power of 2,
and I've got no representation in binary
of the fractional part of this number.
In this case, I picked an easy example.
0.375, if I multiply it by 2 to the third, or 8,
that's going to get me a 3 in decimal.
I can then use what I just did as my trick
to convert that to binary.
That's 11.
And then I divide by 2 to the third, which simply says
shift it right three points.
And there is the binary representation
of that decimal fraction.
That's cool, right?
It's a really neat idea.
What am I doing?
I'm using something I did for one computation,
but converting another problem into the same problem.
In this case, given a fraction, I'm
saying find a power of 2 that shifts it into an integer,
use the same machinery, and then shift it back.
And I'm simply taking advantage of powers of 2
because that's simply moving the placeholder, if you like,
for the decimal point, or I should say the binary point
in a binary representation.
There's code that'll do it.
I'm not going to walk through it.
I'm going to let you look at it.
I'm simply going to show you that this will actually convert
a decimal to a binary fraction.
So if I take this and I run it, in this case,
it says give me a decimal between 0 and 1.
Let's pick out a nice example.
Let's start with the one that we had, which was 0.375.
Sorry, let me make sure I'm here.
And it says, oh, I'm going to tell you
when I've gone through it to get it up to something
that is big enough.
How many times I have to shift it over, what's the remainder,
and there's the printed solution.
Let's be daring and try another example
I haven't tried before just to make sure
that it actually works.
So again, we're going to call this out.
It says give me a number between 0 and 1.
And I don't know, let's take 0.333.
And what do I get?
Well, it goes through a whole lot more computation.
It's telling me what the remainders are,
but it's running through that computation.
And it says the binary representation for 0.333
is this horrible-looking mess you see on my computer screen
down there.
But the point of this is now I can take any floating point
number, convert into something that
can be represented inside of the machine in binary form,
and use it.
And that, by the way, is why you will occasionally
see these strange things where you're expecting 3.0 back,
and it has a little bit of an extra piece
on it because in binary it can get close to it,
but not quite to the place it would like.
But with that, we now have a way of understanding
how we can represent floating point numbers inside a machine
where everything is stored just in terms of binary bits.
What are some of the implications of this?
If there is no integer p such that a power of 2
multiplied by x gives me a whole number,
then the best I'm going to get is an internal representation
that's close.
Which is why I won't get something exactly right.
And obviously, I'm only going to do this so many times
before I run out of powers of p to use this.
It also suggests that when you want
to test equality of floats, you should be careful.
Given two floats, x and y, you really
don't want to use double equal sign,
because it's going to check to see
is the binary representation exactly the same.
It might not be.
It might be really close.
So we're always better off using the absolute value
of the difference of two floating point numbers.
Is it smaller than some small number,
rather than using the more exact are they exactly the same.
And then finally, as I've already said,
we may not always get an exact representation
for a float in the way we would like.
But if I do print of something, why does
it always return what I'd expect,
even if the representation isn't different?
And the answer is because, wonderfully, the designers
of Python designed it so that it would automatically
round to the closest representation in terms
of that floating point number.
There are floats.
Now we've got ability to do integers and floats,
we're in good shape.