...
We just saw an example where we walked through carefully
the execution or the invocation of a function
called a factorial in order to see
how the different scoped frames were created
and to help us sort of decide that, in fact, it
will stop when it reaches a base case and return a value.
But when I start trying to design code,
I have to think about the same thing--
how do I set it up so that I know
it's actually going to stop?
How do we know a recursive code is going to work?
In the case of an iteration, we know that
by making sure that we've got a loop invariant that
changes as we go through it in order to make sure
that we actually get down to a place where we hit the end
test.
So mult inter terminates because b is initially positive,
and it decreases by 1 each time through.
I've set that up by making sure I change it by 1.
And so I know eventually it's got to get down to a place
where it's less than 1, which is going to trigger that n clause.
And I can use that to deduce that I've
written code that is, in fact, going to terminate if I give it
an appropriate set of values.
What about the recursive version?
Sorry, as I said, mult is called with b1,
in that it has no recursive call, and it stops.
But how do I know that it stops in general?
Well, if I call mult where b is greater than 1,
it makes a recursive call with a smaller version of b.
And so, again, I know that eventually it
must reach a call where b is equal to 1.
This tells me that when I write a recursive version
of a function, I need to make sure that I'm
changing the parameter.
In this case, this value, so that I'm
going to get down to that test case.
That's nice, but there's another way in which, in fact, I
could reason about my code to decide,
is it going to, in fact, terminate
or is it going to get into an infinite loop,
because it's going to recursively call itself
over and over again?
And to do that, we can use, as a little sidebar,
a nice little mathematical tool called mathematical induction.
Here's the idea behind induction.
If I want to prove a statement that
is indexed on integers, that is, it's
a statement that is applied to a set of integers.
If I want to prove that statement
is true for all values of some parameter n,
I just need to prove that it's true
when n has it's smallest value.
For example, n is equal to 0 or 1.
And then I need to prove that if it is true on an arbitrary
value of n, I can also then show that it
must be true for n plus 1.
And with that, I can then essentially
deduce mathematically, that it's true for all values of n.
Let me show you a little mathematical example of this.
The sum of the integers for 0 up to n,
I claim as n times n plus 1 divided by 2.
If n is 1, it says 1 times 2 over 2 is 1.
If it's 2, 1 plus 2 is 3, and 2 times 3 divided by 2 is 3.
You get the idea.
How would I prove this is actually a true statement?
Well, the proof says take the simplest case.
If n is equal to 0, what do I have?
Then the left-hand side is just 0,
and the right-hand side is 0 times 1 divided by 2,
which is just 0.
So it's true.
To prove it in general, I simply assume
it's true for some value-- let's call it k.
And then I need to show that it's true for k plus 1.
So I need to show that this statement is true.
Well, but that's nice, because the left-hand side,
I know that it's true for that.
I just assume that.
I know that in that case, that is
k times k plus 1 divided by 2.
So the left-hand side is simply that, by that assumption.
And if I do just a little bit of algebra,
I can show that that is, in fact, the same as this,
and I'm done, having proved it.
Assuming k, therefore it's true for k plus 1,
I can now say it's true for all values of n.
So this formula is always true.
What does that have to do with code?
Well, I can do the same thing.
Here, with my case of a recursive call to mult,
I need to do the following-- I need
to show the base case is true.
Will this true return the right answer when b is equal to 1?
Yep.
Now, what about in the recursive case?
I'm going to assume that my code does
the right thing for smaller versions of the problem,
meaning that I'm going to assume that mult returns
the right answer.
And, in that case, I can then say on this piece of code,
if it does the right thing, then this return does
the right thing, because it's simply an addition.
So in that case, I know it returns the right answer
for a problem of size b.
And by mathematical induction, my code
will always do the right thing for appropriate values
of a and b.
Thus induction tells me I've got code that works.