We've seen some simple examples of recursion,
factorial, doing multiplication by doing recursive addition.
These are nice places to start.
But recursion is actually really a powerful tool.
And I want to show you a very different way of thinking
about recursion on a problem that's
otherwise hard to solve if you don't
think about it recursively.
And this is to take a classic problem called
the Towers of Hanoi.
The story is that somewhere in the temple in Hanoi
there are three tall spikes on which there are initially
64 disks of different sizes all stacked together
in decreasing order with the largest at the bottom
going all the way up to having the smallest at the top.
And the goal of the priests in this temple
is to move the entire stack from one spike
to another one, moving one disk at a time,
but with the property that they can never
have a larger disk covering up a smaller disk.
And there's a little animation you
may be watching at the bottom here
that's showing an example of that
with a stack of size three.
We want to figure out how would I write a program
to tell the priests exactly how to move those disks so they
can move all 64 from one spike to the other.
And I'm going to do a little demo to show that to you.
So I want to demonstrate for you how to solve Towers of Hanoi
and especially how to use recursive thinking to do that.
But to begin with, I'm simply going to show you solutions
to Towers of Hanoi and see if you can figure out
how to write code to describe the set of moves
that would solve it.
Let's start with the easiest case.
I have a stack of size one.
Moving it is easy.
I just move the disk.
If I have a stack of size two, I know
I've got to move the higher to the smaller
disk to the spare place while I move the bottom one,
and then move it over-- pretty straightforward.
If I want to move a stack of size three,
takes a little more work because I got to move the top disk.
I got to be careful not to cover up a smaller disk with a larger
one.
But once I've cleared the bottom disk,
I can move it, and, again, move the top disk to the spare one
so that I move the entire thing without covering up a smaller
disk with a larger disk-- also pretty easy.
But what about a stack of size four.
It takes a little more thinking because I
have to really be careful here that I'm not accidentally
covering things off.
And it takes a lot more work to, in fact,
expose that bottom disk, which I'm now ready to move.
And now I've got to get all of those back over again
without covering a smaller disk with a larger one.
And so that allows me, basically,
to make that set of moves to get to that point.
Great-- easy to write code to do this.
Right?
Probably not.
But if I think about it recursively, it's really easy.
So what does that mean?
I want to move a stack of N disks.
And recursively, I would say if I already
knew how to move a smaller stack, what's my solution?
Oh, that's easy.
Move a slightly smaller stack to the spare disk.
Now I can move the bottom disk and move
that stack to the target.
And what does it mean to move that stack to the target?
Move a slightly smaller stack to the spare disk,
move the bottom one, and move that stack.
And I'll just keep on winding that until I'm just
moving single disks.
Recursively, this is easy to see.
And that leads to a very natural implementation.
OK.
What you saw in that demo is that it's
going to be hard, even if you watch things
like moving a stack of three or stack of four.
How would you write the code to do it?
And then what you saw is if I think about it recursively,
it's actually really easy.
Because recursively, what do I do?
I solve a smaller problem.
Move a stack of size N minus 1 onto the spare disk.
Then I've got just one disk left on the bottom of it.
I move that one, which is a simpler problem.
And then I move that stack that I just temporarily
moved to the other side back on to the place I'm going to.
Recursively, this is really easy to see.
And so even though this looked like a very hard problem,
it's very easy to write code to do it.
And so there is, in fact, a little set of code
that says-- I got a function that simply
says print an individual move from the from stack
to the to stack.
And then here, notice what I've got I've got.
I've got a test for a base case.
If I've got just a stack of size one,
I'm just going to print the move to take it from from to to.
Otherwise, I actually now have to solve
two recursive problems.
So it's a little bit different.
I'm going to move a smaller stack from to
from to the spare swap.
Having done that, I'm going to move
the simple case to the place I'm trying to go to.
And then I got to move another smaller size
stack from the spare over to the to spot.
But the code itself is really straightforward.
And if in fact I go and run this on a stack of size four,
it gives me very nicely all of the moves
I want to do to move that stack over.
What I want you to see here are two things.
One, I can have multiple recursive calls
inside of a function body.
It's perfectly fine.
And two, this is a problem that I suggest
is really hard to solve iteratively,
but elegantly easy to solve recursively.
And I want you to think about the notion of break it down
into a smaller version of the same problem,
assume that can be solved, build your solution with that
and other simple operations, and let the recursion then
unwind it to get to the solution that you want.