...
Now that we have the ability to create functions,
to define our own functions, we're
going to be able to start solving
some really neat problems, including some of the ones
we just looked at.
But one of the things that's going to happen
is that we're going to be able to create lots of functions.
And that means that we need to think about how to handle them.
So far we've assumed that all of our code is stored in one file.
And that's cumbersome when I've got large collections of code,
or especially when I've got a collection of code that's
going to be used by different people in different places
and I'd like to be able to access it directly.
And so for that we're going to introduce something
you're going to use a lot.
It's called a module.
And basically a module is a Python file that has something
with a .py extension to it that's a collection of Python
definitions of statements.
Once I've got that module I can use it.
And I need to talk briefly about how do you use it.
So for example, imagine I've created
a little file called circle.pi.
It's a Python file called circle and it's
got in it a couple of simple functions for dealing
with properties of circles-- compute the area,
compute the circumference.
Also put a definition of Pi inside of there.
I've saved that file away and now I want to use it.
How might I use it?
Well I can import it.
I can either import it into the shell itself or I could import
it in fact into some other file, because I want to use it there.
And so the usage here is if I can invoke the command import
circle, it goes and finds that file
and reads all of the statements, including the definitions
and assignments inside that file, into in this case
the shell.
Now inside of the shell I could redefine Pi to be 3.
That's OK, because I'm walking inside the shell.
I could print that out, and in that case
it's going to print out 3.
But then I could print out the value of Pi
that was defined in the module circle.
And to do that I use this notation here of circle
with a dot followed by pi.
It's telling me in the module circle look up the value of Pi.
And that will print out what I defined there-- 3.14159.
And similarly I could call the function defined in circle.
Again, the dot that says inside of the circle module
get the function called area and call it on an argument 3
and it prints out something.
And the same thing with circumference.
So I can import things into my environment, whether again it's
the shell or as we'll see later on inside
of another environment or it's right inside of another file
itself because I want to use it there.
If I don't want to refer to the functions and variables
by their module.
If I don't want to use that slightly clunky circle.pi
or circle.area and I know that the names in that module
don't collide with things I'm using directly,
either inside the shell or inside of a new function,
I can in fact do a slightly different version
in which I say from a module, in this case circle,
import everything.
And the everything is done by simply giving it a star.
That will bring all of the definitions, all
of the assignments, into that environment,
but now I simply refer to them by their name.
I don't have to put that extra circle dot in front of them.
This has the effect of creating bindings
within the current scope for all of the objects defined
within circle.
And the statements, as a consequence, within a module
are executed only the first time a module is imported.
If I want to redo something I have
to recall that actual invocation.
But that gives me a nice way to start
building modularity of a higher scale
by files as well as by functions.
And that leads to the last piece we're
going to deal with today, which is we need a way to save
our work for later use.
And we certainly have that if we do something inside of the text
editor, but we also want to be able to do
that inside of computations we're doing.
Every operating system on a computer
has its own way of handling files,
and so Python handles by providing an operating
system independent way of accessing files
called a file handle.
And the way that is done is by using the special command open
and giving it the name of a file and giving it a command.
So in this particular case, open is
going to open up a file handle, that is an access into a file,
with the name kids and the W here
says that it's opened for writing.
I'm going to be able to write into it.
And I've bound that to a name so I can refer to it.
Name handle is the handle that gets into that file.
That allows me then to use it.
So for example, I could write a little loop that
says to the user, type in a name,
and I'll write it into that file.
By again using name handle and the dot and then the
write command.
And this little extra character here
is a string that just says do a carriage return
or start a new line after the end of this right.
I could do it as many times as I want.
In this case it was just going to be two times,
but what I'm doing is I'm writing directly into a file,
in this case called kids, things that I'm
inputting on the terminal.
You can imagine also doing computations and writing them
away.
When I'm done, I close the file handle
by invoking the method close.
Again with name handle, because that's
the one I set up up here, dot close.
And the open close paren to say that it's actually
an invoking of a function that closes up the file.
And finally, I can do the same thing
where I want to read from a file by giving it the special string
R. And in this case I could read from that file
and just print out a set of things,
and when I'm done again close them off.
So this gives you a little bit more power now.
And it's part of that idea of modularity.
I have functions giving me modularity.
I can have collections of functions inside of files.
I can create files as I'm interacting with them.
And I can use all of those ideas to really control
the complexity of the systems that I'm building.