...
So how do we create this notion of abstraction
and decomposition in Python, or actually
in any programming language?
And the answer is, we introduced the idea
of a reusable piece of code, or a chunk of code,
called a function.
Functions are not going to be run in a program
until we actually ask them to do that.
So as opposed to things I was typing into my shell--
every time I typed in an expression,
it was invoked or evaluated-- I'm
going to create a definition of a function.
And when I read that in, it's simply
going to create the ability to do that computation,
but not actually call it.
And we'll see an example of that in a second.
What are the characteristics of a function?
Several.
First, it has a name.
That makes sense.
I've got to be able to refer to it.
In the same way that I had a variable as a name for a value,
a function will have a name.
It will also take a set of parameters.
These are arguments or values that I'm
going to use inside the function when I do a computation.
It's going to make sense in a second
when we look at an example.
Every function has to have parameters.
But the number of parameters could be zero.
Or it's a funny way of saying, it's
going to take in a parameter list,
but in fact, it may need no parameters.
And I'm going to decide when I create a function how
many parameters I need.
We'd like every function to have a doc string.
That is a documentation that tells me
what the function does.
We'll see an example of that in a second.
And finally, a function has a body.
And the body is the sequence of commands or instructions
that we want to actually have happen
when we use the function.
Those are a lot of words.
Let's look at an example to get a sense of this.
Here's a definition of a function.
And I'm going to walk through each of these pieces.
So the first part of it is I've got a keyword, in this case
def.
And it is a key word, meaning it's
a special symbol to Python that tells me
I'm about to define something.
In this case, I'm about to define a function.
That is followed by a string that
is the name of the function.
In this case, it's is even, or is underscore even.
That's the name I'm going to give to this function.
That is followed in parentheses, in those parens,
by zero, one, or more parameters.
In this case, I've got one.
And I'm giving it a name.
Think of it like a variable name.
Well, I'm saying, I'm going to use the name
i as the name for a parameter inside this function.
And that's then followed by a colon
to tell me I'm done with the top line of the definition,
I'm about to follow it with other information.
So keyword def, a name, and in parens
some number of parameters.
Immediately below that in triple double quotes--
which is a wonderful expression-- is a docstring.
It's up to you how to use this.
But traditionally, you would specify
what's the input to this function
and what's the output of this function.
It's a little bit like a contract.
In this case, I'm saying I'm expecting one input.
I'm calling it i.
And it's a positive integer.
And what I'm going to return is true if i is even.
Otherwise, I'm going to return false.
As you'll see in a little bit, one
of the nice things about a docstring
is, once I've defined this function, if I go to call it,
which I'm going to get to in a second, Python will
automatically bring up a little window that tells me
the docstring that's remind me what
the conditions for this function are, which is great.
So keyword, name, parameters, I've got a docstring.
Immediately below that is the body of the function.
This is the sequence of commands or expressions
I want to evaluate when I'm ready to use this.
Notice the indentation-- all of this is indented here.
This is telling me where the body of the function is.
And in fact, it will be everything
until I get back to something that
returns to the left hand side of the editor or of the shell.
In this case, I've got two expressions in my body.
It's going to print out simply the string hi.
And then it's going to return a value.
We'll come back to the return in a second.
There is how I write a function.
Now, how do I use it?
The function has a name.
The same way I could use a variable
as a name inside of an expression,
I can use the function name.
And in particular, later on in the code,
I can say an expression like, is underscore even,
and then an open paren, followed by an expression whose value
I'm going to use inside of that procedure
followed, in this case, by a closed paren, because there's
only one parameter.
I call this invoking or calling the function.
I'm using the function.
We're going to look at some examples in a second.
But the basic idea here is that, when I call this function,
I'm going to take the value 3, in this case,
and everywhere I see an i in the body of the function,
I'm going to use that value in place of i.
And in fact, if I look at it then,
inside of this particular expression,
I'm going to print out simple the string hi.
And then I'm going to evaluate this particular expression.
And it has the keyword return followed by an actual value.
Now, I just said, in this case, if I've
called is_even with the parameter 3,
i now holds the value 3.
So I'm going to evaluate 3 remainder 2 and say,
is that equal to 0?
In this case, it's not, because the remainder is 1.
And I'm going to then return that value to whoever
called this function.
So that's the expression I want to evaluate and actually
return.
So return is a keyword that tells me
I'm ready to stop the computation.
And whatever the following expression is,
that is the value I'm going to give back
to the person who asked for it.
In this case, it was simply at my shell.
But we'll see in a second, it could
be somebody else that's going to use it
as part of another computation.