...
This idea of function invocation-- function calling--
is really important.
It's central to how we're going to use
functions to control our code.
So I want to work through in a little more careful detail
exactly what happens when we call a function
and how we get values associated with variables.
You'll see on the screen here, I've
got a little piece of code.
I'm defining a function called f.
I'm binding x to 3, and then I'm going
to call f with the value of x and bind that to z.
Let me show you what happens if I actually run this.
So on my computer, I've got a version of that file.
And I'm going to load it into my shell.
And what it prints out, as you can see, as it says in f of x,
x is equal to 4.
How'd that happen?
What's going on here, because x seems like it's
used in a lot of places?
So this is going to be an important opportunity
to look at how functions are called.
As I've already said, the key idea is each formal parameter--
in this case, I only have one-- is
going to get bound to the value of the actual parameter
when the function is called.
And then when I call a function, I'm
going to create a new environment,
sometimes called a frame or a scope,
a new place in which I'm going to bind variables
and relative to which I'm going to evaluate
the body of the function.
Think of that scope as a mapping of names to objects.
And, in fact, we've been using that idea when we were just
talking to the shell, when we defined
x to have a value of, say, of 5, we were creating
in the global scope or frame a binding of the name
x to the value 5.
Now, let's look at this in a little more careful detail.
Imagine I now do what I just did on my computer.
I evaluate this sequence of expressions.
There is that formal parameter.
There's the actual parameter I'm going to use,
and let's look at what happens.
I evaluate that, and in that global frame,
I create a set of bindings.
First one is evaluating that definition
binds the variable name f to something.
Oh, but that's important, because that something is just
a set of code.
I haven't run f yet.
I haven't tried to do x equals x plus 1 or anything else.
I've literally, in the machine, said associate the name
f with a chunk of stuff.
Next thing I did was I evaluated x equal 3,
and that just creates a binding.
We've seen this before.
So in the global scope, x has a binding to the value of 3.
And now I'm ready to evaluate that last expression, which
says give the name z the value of calling f on x.
And I'm ready to do that.
Now remember, before I can actually do the binding of c,
I have to get the value of that expression.
So calling f literally creates a new scope, a new frame.
It will actually inherit things from the global frame
if it needs it, but right now I've got a new environment.
The definition of x has a formal variable
x, and that's exactly what that corresponds to.
And the value associated with it is
the value of x that I passed in, which actually came from there.
I know it looks a little confusing.
I'm deliberately using two different values
of x so you can see where the bindings come from.
So f evaluated on x says, what is the value of x?
I get it from the binding that I just did previously.
So inside that f scope, x is bound to 3.
Now, relative to that scope, I'm going
to evaluate the body of f.
I want to do the work that f says it's going to do.
So let me see what happens there.
First expression says, evaluate x plus 1,
and I'm actually going to go back for a second.
Remember, in the f scope, x has the binding of 3.
I add 3 plus 1, that 4, and I create a new binding
for x but in the f scope, because that's
where I'm doing the work.
So it changes it here.
It does not change the thing that
was out in the global frame.
That's great.
Now, relative to that, I'm going to print out something,
and on my computer screen you saw
it said, in f of x, x is equal to-- ah--
the value of x in the f scope.
And that's why it printed out 4.
And then what it's going to do is it's going to return x.
So literally it's going to get the value of x
in the f scope, which is 4, and it's
going to return it to the person who asked for it.
And what was that person?
That was down here.
We're doing the binding of z.
So I've just returned to that binding,
a value for f of x, which is 4, and that
creates the binding for z.
If this is a little confusing, watch the same segment again,
because this is an important idea.
Any time I do an evaluate-- sorry, rephrase
that-- any time I do an invocation of a function,
I create a new frame.
I bind the formal parameter of that function, or parameters
if there is more than one, to the values
of the expressions passed in.
And relative to that frame, I now
evaluate the body of that expression.
When I'm done with the body of the function,
if there's a return, I'm going to send the value back
to whoever called for it and erase or remove that frame
because I no longer need it.
OK.
With that idea, let's look at a couple of other examples.
First, what happens if there is no return statement?
Here's my function from before-- is even.
But rather than returning is the remainder of i divided
by 2 equal to 0, I just have the expression.
So there's no return here.
What happens in this case is that Python returns the value
none, because I did not give a return.
So Python will say in a function call,
if you don't have an explicit return,
I return the none value.
It represents the absence of a value,
and unfortunately that would mean, in this case,
I would not get back the answer of true or false.
I would simply print out nothing, because there's
nothing to be returned.
Point of this is, any time I want
a function to do something, unless it's simply
doing something we call a side effect,
I always want to have at least one return that's
going to give a value back.
So remember to keep your returns in.
In fact, that gives me a chance to talk about the difference
between return and print.
You can see the description here,
and let's just do it quickly.
Return only has a meaning inside a function.
It's the only place we can use it, inside a function.
I could have more than one return.
If I have branches or other conditionals,
I might have different places from which I want a return.
But only one return will ever be executed inside the function,
because it's going to throw me outside of the function
and return a value.
Any code inside the function but after the return statement
will never be executed.
And of course, a return does have
a value associated with it.
It's given back to the person who called the function.
By comparison, while return has a meaning only
inside a function, a print can certainly
be used inside a function, but it can also
be used outside of a function.
We've already seen that.
We can also execute many print statements inside a function.
And any code inside the function after that print statement
can, in fact, be executed.
Again, a print has a value associated with it,
but it is simply output directly onto the console
rather than being returned.
So prints are going to be handy to have us pass information
back to the user to let them know
the status of a computation.
Return is the way in which I'm going
to get a value back to somebody who asked for it, whether it's
me as the user or some other function call.
With that in mind, let's look at,
in fact, how you might have other function calls.
So not only can parameters have numerical values,
they could also have another values,
including being a function.
So I have three definitions of functions here.
The first one, A, takes no parameters.
I've said this earlier, but I'm going to say it again.
Notice it has an open and close paren.
That's important.
I have to tell it that there are no parameters there.
Function B takes one parameter, in this case called y.
And function C also takes one parameter, in this case it's z.
What's interesting about this is how these functions
are going to use them.
And in a second, I'm going to run it.
But notice I'm going to call function A with no parameter.
So an open and close paren to tell me there
are no parameters.
I'm going to call function B. It's
going to take in one parameter.
In this case, I'm going to give it a number.
And function C is going to take in one parameter,
but in this case it's another function.
Whoa.
That's funky.
It's actually OK.
I can pass in the name of the function,
and that will literally pass the actual function
in to that parameter call for function C.
Let's see what happens if we try this.
So I've got that code loaded up over here.
I'm going to pass it into my computer.
And notice what it printed out.
The first thing is it printed out inside function A.
That came from calling this function,
and that's the print statement right there.
There is no return in function A.
And so, in fact, the print takes the value returned
by function A, which was none, and it printed it out
on my computer.
I then take the next call.
I pass into the function B. Function B
prints inside function B right there,
which is the next thing it did.
And then it returns the value passed in, which
is the value of y, which is 2.
That gets out at the 5, which is why on my machine
I printed out 7.
The print statement printed out 7.
And then the last one, again, a little funky.
I passed in function A as an argument for z in function C.
And what happened?
It printed out inside function C,
and then it called a return of calling z with no arguments.
And what's z?
It's function A. Oh, that's nice, because function A then
said print out inside function A, which it did.
Return nothing, because there is no return statement.
And so this print at the bottom then printed out none.
We could step through it more carefully,
but you hopefully get the idea.
In each case, I'm simply evaluating the body
with respect to a frame.
And the arguments could, in fact,
be other functions that I can invoke inside
of a function call, which I did inside of function C.
So as a consequence, inside of a function,
we can both access a variable defined outside
as well as a variable defined inside.
On the other hand, inside of a function,
we can't modify a variable that's
defined outside of the scope of that function.
And here I have three little examples just
to give you a sense of that.
What I'm going to do is show you basically
what would happen for each one of these function calls.
So I've defined f of x to be set x equal to 1, add 1 to x,
and then print out the value of x.
I've define g to simply say print x,
and then print x plus 1.
And I've defined h to have a body that
says simply increment x by 1.
And I want to think about what do those things actually do?
Well, let's look at each of those examples.
In each case, I'm going to define x to have the value 5.
I'm going to call the function with that value of x,
and then I'm going to print out x.
What happens?
In the case of f of x, x as 5 is passed in.
I redefine x to be 1 inside of there.
And then I add 1 to that value of x, which is 2,
and then I print out x.
So, in fact, f of x is going to print out the value 2.
And then this print statement is going to print out the value 5.
Why?
Because it sees the value of x defined in the global scope,
which is where I am.
What happens in the case of g? g says-- well, first of all,
I called g with the value of x, which
is 5, which means 5 is going to be used in place of y.
And then I say print x.
Hmm.
You say, wait a minute.
There is no x as a parameter to g.
That's fine, because it then says
if I can't find it in the frame associated with g,
let me look outside.
And there is a value, which is 5.
So in this case, it's going to print 5,
then it's going to print 6, which is x plus 1.
It has no return.
So it's not going to do anything else.
And then I'm going to print the value
of x, which I get from here, the global environment.
And it's going to print 5.
Finally, I define h of y.
I've done that.
I've defined x to be 5, and now I call h with the value of y
being 5.
And what do I do?
I'm going to print out-- sorry, not that.
Rephrase that.
I'm going to try and define x to be x plus 1.
And let's think about what happens.
So just to go back to this, I've already
defined x from outside g.
That's why I pick up that scope.
What happens in the case of h?
Oh, I got an unbound variable error,
because I'm trying to look up the local variable value of x.
I'm referencing it before I've assigned it.
So, in fact, I'm going to complain about this,
and I'm not going to succeed.
So we can see, I can look up values outside the scope,
but I can't change the values of those things
outside of the scope appropriately.
And that's a place where I have to be
careful about how I actually use these different procedures.
Three different examples shows you different ways
in which we can deduce how we actually pick up
the values of the variables.
In each case, as I said, the x comes
from the global or main program scope
when I print out this value at the bottom down here.
I'm going to show you one more example of scoping.
I want to do a quick aside, which
says when you get to really tricky things,
there's a nice place to go look, which
is this place on the web called the Python Tutor that helps
you sort these pieces out.
And the last example, before we move on to other topics,
is to look at something that actually has a function defined
inside another function.
Wow, that sounds neat.
Here I've got a definition for g, and inside of there,
I've got a definition for h.
And if I look at this code, I'm going
to actually run it over here.
Let's see what happens when I run it,
and let's see why it does that appropriate thing.
And when I ran it, it prints out the statement
inside g of x, x bound to 4.
And I want to see how that comes about.
So here we go.
When I evaluate or when I just, in fact,
evaluate it inside my machine, this description, here's
what happened.
As I saw before, in the global environment,
g was bound to a bunch of code.
Where is h?
It hasn't happened yet.
It's simply sitting in a chunk of code.
We have not yet evaluated that body.
So nothing has happened yet.
x is bound to 3.
So when I get to the point shown by the arrow here,
this point in the code, I've got g as some code.
I've got x bound to the value 3.
Now I'm ready to do a binding for z to be a call to g.
We saw it happen before.
g creates a new scope, and inside of that scope
I'm going to bind the value of x.
And that x is coming from the formal parameter for g.
The value is coming from the binding
for x in the global scope.
So x is bound to 3.
And then I'm going to evaluate the body of g.
And this is cool, because that says inside of here,
I'm evaluating the definition of h.
This is sometimes called an internal or helper function,
because it belongs only to g.
The binding for h right here is to some set of code.
Only when I'm inside of g can I use h.
It's protected.
That's great.
Haven't used it yet.
I've just got a binding for h.
And then what do I do?
I create a binding for x, and notice what happened.
I say get the current value of x, which was 3, add 1 to it,
and then change the binding for x in the scope of g,
because that's where I'm doing the work.
So it's changed that binding for x but not this one
over here, which is still 3.
And then I do the print statement,
which is why it says in g of x, x has got the value 4.
Because, in fact, I see this value of x over here.
All right.
Almost done.
Now I'm going to call h.
How?
H is a function.
It's right there.
And since I'm invoking it, I create a new scope.
And this scope inherits from g, which inherited
from the global scope.
Inside of h, I bind any formal parameters.
There aren't any.
What do I do?
I evaluate the body of h.
So I bind x to the string abc, and then what do I return?
Oh, yeah.
Nothing.
Because I have no return statement.
So having done that binding for x, I'm done with the call to h,
and there is nothing to return.
Having done that, I'm now ready to do the last part of g,
which was to return x.
And you notice that binding inside of h, of x equal to abc,
it's gone.
It's been garbage collected.
And so I now simply return the value x, which I know
is defined inside the scope of g.
And that gets returned as the value that I associate with z.
Perfect.
I'm now set, because z has the binding 4.
So there is a more complicated example,
but you notice how those rules for scopes
very nicely tell me and, more importantly,
tell Python exactly how to look up values
and how to use those to store new values as I do bindings.