...
Now that we've introduced the idea
of a definition, a function in particular,
as a way of doing encapsulation of information,
we can start exploring some of the variations to them.
And I want to show you one place in Python this actually
can be very handy.
And that is that I can have a function definition
that I can change in terms of how I want
to think about invoking it.
So let's start with a simple function here.
This is a very simple function that
says if the last argument is true,
then I'm going to print the last name comma first name.
Otherwise I'm going to print the first name comma followed
by the last name.
And I'm going to expect those to be strings.
And I've got a simple little implementation over here.
I'm going to import it into my Python shell so I can use it.
But at this stage, you can hopefully look at this function
and realize, given some value for reverse,
I'm going to test that.
If it's true, I'm going to do this, which is just to print.
It's not going to return anything.
If it's false, I'm going to do that.
OK?
Now, here's one of the nice variations on it.
First of all, that first call does what I'd expect.
And, in fact, if I go to my Python and type
it in, I can say if I do print name--
and I'll do myself-- of Eric Grimson,
and I give false as a value for reverse,
it prints it out in the order I expect it.
I could do, by the way, the same thing.
I could say print name just to show you
it does the right thing of Eric and Grimson.
Notice the commas, by the way, to separate the parameters.
And I give it true.
It would help if I can type.
So I'll do it one more time with Eric Grimson and true.
Now it prints it out in the other order.
But here are some of the variations.
I could say explicitly give the binding to the parameter
name reverse the value false.
So doing it in the same place, but I can actually specify it.
I could similarly for any of the parameters in the invocation
literally say the parameter followed by an equal sign
and the value that I want.
And all three of these are going to print out
exactly the same thing.
And, in fact, so will the last one.
But notice here I have reversed the order.
So if I'm not going to use this kind of formalism,
I have to give the parameter in the place it expects.
But in this case, I reversed it.
Even though the function expects first name then last name,
I've said I'm going to have last name have the binding
Grimson, first name have the binding Eric,
and reverse equal to false.
That's nice if I forget the order
or if I just decide I want to call them in a different way.
I can do some other things here though.
I can change the definition of my function to give a default
value to one of the parameters.
In this case, the syntax is there's the parameter name,
and I'm saying let it have initially the binding of false.
And that means that if I call the function, as I do right
here, without an explicit parameter passed in,
or value passed in for that parameter,
the default holds true.
In this case, I'm going to assume that reverse is false,
and therefore I'm going to do this particular print
statement.
Now, on the other hand, if I want
to change the value of that, I need
to give it an explicit value to overwrite the default value.
And this is handy if I've got a parameter that normally I
expect just to have a particular value, but on a rare occasion
I might want to change it, my invocations
don't have to always pass in those values.
So a nice little variation on how we pass
values into parameters of definitions of functions.