...
In that last example, we looked at how using a dictionary
could let us make computation much more efficient.
We store away computed values that we
want to reuse so we simply look them up.
Nice idea.
To demonstrate it I showed you some examples
of running the code.
And we simply used the delay in time
before we printed out a result to try and get
a sense of how different the efficiencies were of that.
I'd like a little more formal way of doing that.
And I'm going to show you an example using
what we call a global variable.
Now I'm going to preface this by saying this
is a dangerous thing to do.
Globals are something that most computer scientists don't
like to use because they can really lead to side
effects in a very bad way.
But in some cases they're valuable, and this is one.
They're dangerous to use because global variables break
the scoping of variables that we get by a function call.
What do I mean by that?
Remember when we were looking at a recursive function
and we call fact on something, and it would call fact
on a smaller argument, and that would create a separate scope.
And the value of the parameter in that scope
was the one we would use.
And it would be different from the value of the parameter
in a different scope.
With global variables we're going
to have the ability to move that value,
that access to that variable, out of scopes.
And that's why it's dangerous to do.
It also allows for side effects because we
can change variable values in ways
that affect other computation.
But it's going to be really handy if we just
want to keep track of the information
inside of a function.
And I want to go back to my example of Fib
and Fib efficient to show you how that would work.
I'm going to take those two definitions
and I'm just going to change them slightly.
In particular, I'm going to add in a variable that
is going to just keep track of how often do I actually
call this function.
And so, I'm first going to say, that variable is global.
And this is simply a statement.
Notice global is a special term.
It says this variable name is something
that I can access outside the scope of the function.
I'll remind you, before this anything
inside the body of the function was only accessible
within the call of the function itself.
But this is something we're going
to be able to see up, for example,
at top level of the global environment.
And then, what I want to do with both of these functions
is simply increment them each time I call them.
It's going to keep track of how often did
I actually call this function.
The rest of it is just like before.
It is exactly what I did when I did these two computations.
So with that small change I can now
track the efficiency of this particular pair of functions.
I'm going to need to initialize that global variable outside.
I'm going to set it to zero.
And then what I'm going to do, for example,
is I'm going to call Fib on an argument like 12,
and then print out a string and the number of times
I called that function.
Because inside that function-- and I'm
going to go back to that previous slide for a second--
it's going to update that variable each time I call it.
I'll then re-initialize it to zero,
I'll set up my dictionary, and I'll do the same thing with Fib
efficient.
And it's going to give me a chance to measure,
in fact, how different are these two functions in terms of how
many times are they called.
So I have on my computer then those two functions.
I'm going to do exactly that.
I'm going to start with something
a little smaller, which is 12.
And I've just got a variable here, fibArg.
So I can just change that rather than changing it
in both places.
And let's see what happens if we call this.
OK, it ran it and it said basically
I got 233 as the answer.
But with the inefficient Fibonacci
there were 287 calls to that function.
With the efficient one, because I'm keeping track of what
I've done, only 21.
All right.
Sounds pretty good.
Let's go back to the one that we used
to see a bigger difference.
Let's go to say, 30.
And let's call that.
I get the same answer both times,
that's good, but notice the difference.
Wow.
Using the dictionary I only called that function 57 times.
Without the dictionary 1.7 million.
Let's just do one more.
We won't make it too big or we'll be here forever.
But let's, I don't know, make it 34.
And let's call it.
And it's going to take a little while to find that answer
but it will find it, I hope, in a second.
There we go.
The answer is the same.
Look at the difference.
With the dictionary, with keeping track of those answers,
65 calls.
And boy, I've got to eyeball that, 11 billion
in the case of the inefficient Fibonacci.
So dictionaries can be really handy here,
and here's a great example of that.
As we go forward, we're going to use dictionaries
in a lot of different ways to really efficiently capture
and use information.
Especially the idea of being able to index
on arbitrary keys.
Something we're going to want to be
able to use as we generalize the kinds of procedures
we're going to compute.