...
Let me show you an example of using a dictionary-- actually
of creating and then using a dictionary.
And I'm going to use an example of simply wanting
to analyze song lyrics.
I want to see how often does a word appear in a lyric,
for example.
So I'm going to write three functions to do this.
They're reasonably straightforward functions.
And it's going to let you see how
we use dictionaries to capture information in a valuable way.
So first I'm going to create a frequency dictionary that's
going to map strings to integers.
The idea is a given set of lyrics for a song.
I'm going to walk down it and for each word-- each string--
I'm going to count basically how many times it actually
appears inside of that lyric.
So the dictionary is going to be that association of a word
and number of appearances.
And once I've created that dictionary,
then I can do things like find the word that
occurs the most often and how many times it does that.
Here I'm going to use a list in case
there's more than one word that occurs
the same number of times.
And so I'm going to return a tuple-- another data
structure-- that has inside of it a list for the set of words
and an integer for how often did that set
of words, each one of them, appear inside the lyrics.
And then finally, I'm going to find the words that occur
at least some number of times.
I'm going to let the user choose that minimum amount.
So it will be a parameter.
And then I'm going to return a list of tuples, where
each tuple is one of those list int combinations
that contains the list of words ordered by their frequency.
And one of the things I'm going to do here
is take advantage of a property of the dictionaries.
From the song dictionary, I'm going
to find the most frequent word, and then I'm
just going to delete it.
And I'm going to repeat.
And because I'm mutating the song dictionary as I do it,
it's going to actually pull together very
nicely an efficient way to solve this problem.
So let's start with the first stage.
I need to create a dictionary.
Here's a function that will do it.
I'm going to call it lyrics to frequencies--
sounds reasonable.
Lyrics will just be a string of words
separated by spaces, potentially other kinds of things.
I'm going to create an empty dictionary.
There are the curly braces that do that.
And then I'm going to just iterate over the lyrics,
getting each word out as I do it.
And what I'm going to do is say, if the word is already
in the dictionary-- and oh, there's that nice thing.
I'm using the fact that I can treat the dictionary
as an iterable. I can just say if the word's already
in the dictionary, increase the value associated
with it by one.
Oh, that says I've already got a value there somewhere.
And that's OK, because it says if the word is not
in the dictionary, this is the first time I've seen the word.
I'm going to set the value in the dictionary corresponding
to that word to one.
And once I've gone through that entire loop,
I'll simply return the dictionary.
On my computer I've got a version of that code
and I've got a song.
Now, even though I used Justin Bieber earlier on,
I'm of a different generation.
I like The Beatles.
So I've got a classic old Beatles song, "She Loves You."
It's also a nice song because it's
got a lot of repetition of the characters in it.
And I've got the entire lyrics to "She Loves You" actually
set up over here.
And so now what I'm going to do is
I'm going to actually load this and run it.
And when I do that, I'm going to basically say,
what does Beatles look like?
And Beatles was set up to be the lyrics to frequencies called on
"She Loves You."
And there's a piece of it.
It's actually much longer than you'd
expect because it's got-- just to show you all the pieces
there, there are all the words in "She
Loves You" as a dictionary associated
with their frequency.
OK.
With that in mind, I've now got a dictionary of frequencies.
That's pretty cool.
What else do I need to do?
Just to remind you, I can iterate over the list.
I can iterate over the dictionary.
Those are really handy things to do.
I can update a value associated with key-- all things that I
wanted to be able to do inside of that dictionary.
Second thing I want to do now is I
want to find the most common words given the dictionary's
input.
So here's how I will do that.
First thing I'm going to do is I'm going to get the values out
from that dictionary.
Values is a method, so I'm going to call it with the open close
paren.
And that gives me back a set of values.
I know those values are all ints.
So I can get the most common number very easily.
I just apply max to values.
I want to stop here for a second because I
want to point out a nice thing.
I could have written an iterative loop that
walked down this, trying to keep pack
of what's the best number I've seen so far updating
as I went along.
It's a perfectly reasonable way to write the code.
But it would've generated a lot of code.
It would have made it harder to read.
Here, in two lines, I've captured the idea I want.
Give me all the values in the dictionary.
Ah, it's now a collection of integers.
Just give me the maximum value.
Really nice.
Now that I know the best, I need to find all the words that
have that value.
And here I will write the iterative loop.
I'm going to set words up initially to be an empty list.
And then for everything in the dictionary, I'm going to check.
Is that entry-- does that entry have the value best?
In other words, is it one of the most common words?
And if it is, oh, there's that nice mutation of words.
Just add it to the end of the list.
And when I'm done, I'm just going to return words and best.
So over here, I've got my Beatles
as that set of frequencies.
And so I could say give me WNB.
I know it's going to return a tuple
to be most common words in what I already did
as the analysis of that song.
And it says, the most common words that occur in that song--
not particularly surprising-- "a," "like," "her," and "with."
And how often do they occur?
They each occur four times.
So I've just found that out.
That sounds pretty good.
Now what else could I do with this?
Well, I said I wanted to find the places in which they occur
most often and find all of those that occur
more than some amount of time.
So the last function I'm going to do here
is I'm going to create a function that says, find
words that occur often in this.
Again, I'm going to set up an empty list initially.
And here I'm going to create a little flag.
And the flag is initially set default
because I'm going to run through a loop here.
And the loop says, as long as I've still got something to do,
here's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to find, as I just did,
the most common words in the dictionary.
And if they occur more than the minimum number of times
that I've set, I'm going to add them into my result.
And then for everything in that word,
I'm going to remove it from the dictionary.
So let me say it again.
I'm going to say, given I've done the analysis,
find the most common word.
I don't know how many times it occurs,
but I'm going to find them.
As long as they occur more than the minimum
I've set, then I'm going to collect those,
because that's part of what I want to have.
And then I'm going to remove them from the dictionary.
So I'm mutating the dictionary right here,
which is really nice.
Because once I've done that, I could go back around and do it
again.
And I'm going to keep doing that until when I pull out
the most common words, they don't exceed my threshold.
In which case I'm going to set that flag to true, which
means when I go back around to the loop,
it's going to say, oh, I'm done.
And I'm going to simply return the result.
And if I do that over here, in fact,
what I get-- if I do words often of Beatles
and I want everything that occurs more than five times
in that structure, huh, I get nothing.
Now, that's a puzzle.
And why is it a puzzle?
And the puzzle is because I did something
that I should have remembered I did.
And that is that I actually processed this multiple times.
So let me start again by going back to this file
and reloading it, because I actually mutated the structures
as I went through them.
And that's why when I said what were the most common words,
it was just "a," "like," "her," and "with" only occurring
four times.
I'd already changed the structure.
Now if do it the right way, you see, ah, not surprisingly,
what occurs most often in "She Loves You"?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
The word "you," 36 times.
The word "yeah," 28 times.
"She," 20 times.
"Love," 13, and so on.
All right, early Beatles weren't very
imaginative with their lyrics.
But what you've seen is how I can use a dictionary
to in fact do analysis, take advantage
of the iterable structure of the dictionary.
And if you think about the three functions I wrote here,
they're very simple.
They're very crisp.
And they very nicely capture exactly the computation
I wanted to do.