...
Let me show you one other place where
a dictionary is an incredibly valuable thing to have.
And to do that, I'm to go back to a piece of code
that we looked at a while ago.
Fibonacci was counting the number of bunnies in a pen.
Remember Fibonacci-- it had two base cases,
it said if n is equal to 1.
The value is 1.
If n is equal to 2, the value is 2.
Otherwise, the nth Fibonacci number
is the sum of the n minus first and n minus second Fibonacci
number.
It calls itself twice.
It has to because it has to do that computation.
And it will certainly work, but this code
is actually very inefficient.
And let me show you why.
Think about what happens if I want to compute fib of, say.
5.
To compute the fifth Fibonacci number,
I need to compute the fourth Fibonacci
number and the third one.
But to compute the fourth Fibonacci number,
I need to compute the third one, which
needs to get the second one, which then also needs
to get the first one.
Now those two are the base cases.
I've unwrapped it all the way down to that level.
Having got fib of 3, fib of 4 also needs fib of 2.
And that's also a base case.
And then finally, fib of 5 needs fib of 3 as well as fib of 4.
And that's got to do another set of computations.
So building a tree of computations, if you like.
Now why do I say it's inefficient?
I don't need to recompute those.
I already know them.
Well, in the case of fib of 1 and fib of 2,
they're just constants.
But fib of 3, I'm doing a computation
there that I didn't really need to do because I've already
figured it out over here.
And you can imagine if I was doing fib of 6,
it would need fib of 5 and fib of 4.
And down here, there would be a whole bunch of other structures
that included things that I'd already computed.
It's inefficient.
And in fact, it really slows down
when you start trying to compute large Fibonacci numbers.
Here's where the dictionaries can really help us.
Rather than recalculating the same value many times,
let's just keep track of what I've already done.
So here's a nice version of fib that's very efficient.
And it basically says I'm going to compute Fibonacci, the NTH
Fibonacci number, but I'm going to give it a dictionary.
And what I'm going to do is say, if I'm computing this Fibonacci
number for the first time, I'll do the work as I normally
would, and then I'm going to store it into the dictionary.
But if I've already done the work,
just look it up and return it.
So if n is already in the dictionary,
I just look up the value and return it.
Otherwise, I do the recursive call as I would
have done before, compute it.
Having done that, I store that value away in the dictionary,
and I return the answer.
And I'm saving the answer here because I
need to hold onto it in order to be able to return it.
To start this up, I need to give the base
case in the dictionary, so there I go.
I put into the dictionary the first and second Fibonacci
numbers.
And then I can just go ahead and do the work.
This process is sometimes called memoization.
It's a way of creating a memo to yourself that remembers
what you've already done.
And that turns up to be much more efficient.
So let's look at a couple of examples of this.
And so over here, I've got versions of fib and fib
efficient.
I'm going to initialize the dictionary.
Then I'm going to just set up an argument.
Let's say I want to compute for-- let's start
with something simple.
Let's just compute the fifth Fibonacci number.
And I've set up a little print routine
that's going to print them out so you
can see how well it does this.
And if I call this-- oh, I did it really quickly.
And it gives the same answer, which is good.
Now let's give it a little bit bigger number,
and I want to let you watch how long it takes
to do the computation because I'm
going to do the straightforward one and then the efficient one.
There was a little bit of a gap there,
but it was almost the same.
Now, let's give it an even bigger number, which is 30.
Oh, and you notice the pause.
And in fact, if I do one more-- I
don't want to make it too long, but let's make it 34.
And I do this.
It's working on fib.
It's working-- oh.
And fib efficient came about really quickly.
So what that's doing is saying, I
can use the dictionary to hold onto values that I've already
computed that I don't need to recompute.
And it gives me a really efficient way
of doing this computation.