...
We've been showing you a lot of great tools in computation.
We've introduced simple data objects.
We've introduced compound data objects.
We've introduced iteration.
We've introduced recursion.
We've talked about using functions in a variety of ways.
You now have a lot of the tools you need to have in order
to build interesting code.
And in fact, we've been asking to do that in the problem sets
that you have been working on as you've
gone through this course.
But we now come to a place where we have
to be a little more clever.
Because you've probably already experienced problems
with your code.
Bugs have wandered in that you weren't expecting.
They have done things that you didn't
want to have happen inside of the code.
And so we're going to now turn to a question
that every computer programmer faces which
is, how do I test my code?
And when it doesn't work the way I expected it to,
how do I go about debugging it?
And that's what this lecture's going to be all about.
Now one of the things that happens with debugging
is that ideally you write code that's
going to do exactly what you want to do the first time.
But that doesn't tend to happen.
So here's the challenge.
You write a piece of code.
You wanted to just nail it the first time.
And here's a little visual of how you
like to expect it to happen.
Wouldn't you like to be able to park like this young girl?
You'd just nail it exactly right as you zero in
on the right spot.
You'd like your code to do it exactly right the first time.
But the reality is, you set up a very complex piece of code,
and you start it up, and it doesn't quite
do what you want it.
So there's expectation and there's reality.
How do we get away from the thing on the right,
and get to the thing on the left, which is what we really
want to have happen here?
So we aim for high quality.
How do we get it there?
Well, I'm going to give you an analogy with making soup.
I'm going to acknowledge it's a little bit of a queasy analogy,
but bear with me here.
You're making soup in the kitchen,
but bugs keep falling in from the ceiling.
So what do you do to make sure you have good soup?
I don't want to eat soup with bugs in it.
Well, you could check the soup for bugs.
You could keep the lid closed, or you could clean the kitchen.
All good things to do.
And all of them have nice components in fact,
of testing and debugging.
Checking for soup is the discipline of testing.
How do I test my code to see whether it in fact
does what I expect it to do?
Keeping the lid closed is what we call defensive programming.
We're going to talk about that.
It is, how do you structure your code?
How do you write code in a way that plans ahead,
to try and make sure that you avoid the bugs,
or at least detect them before you actually run the code?
And cleaning the kitchen, just eliminate the source of bugs.
Do the debugging to get it done.
That's what we're going to talk about in this lecture.
So defensive programming, at a high level,
basically has three parts.
The first one is to write specifications
for the functions you're writing.
Write out those doc strings that says,
here is what I expect coming in, and here's
what I will deliver if I get things
that are of the right form.
Second nice piece of defensive programming
is to write modular programs.
Don't write one really long huge single function.
Break it up into obvious pieces.
Those pieces are going to be valuable to us
when we get around to actually testing,
because I can test each piece in turn.
And then finally, under defensive programming,
I want to check the conditions on those inputs and outputs.
We're going to see an example of that in a later lecture, where
we use assertions to actually formally do that.
But defensive programming basically
comes down to defining what I expect
to come in what I'll deliver, and then ensuring
that I actually do that.
Testing, or validation, really comes down
to comparing inputs and outputs.
Given a set of functions I want to test,
I should write a list of a set of example inputs,
and what I expect in each case as an output.
And then when I discover it's not working,
figure out how to debug it.
I also want to ask a different kind of question which
is, how can I break my program?
What are the right kinds of inputs
to use to make sure I test all of the different cases that
are going to be important, ensuring that my program is
doing the right thing?
And finally with debugging, once I have a bug,
what do I want to do?
Mostly I want to look at the events that
led up to the error.
What was going on before this error occurred?
And then ask two different kinds of questions.
One, why is it not working?
What's causing that?
And then having found that, how do I go ahead and fix it
so it will work properly?
Those are the tools that we want to have
as we think about testing and debugging our code.