...
So once you're ready to start debugging,
here's some advice that can help you out.
The first one is, I want to start by pointing out that this
is a steep learning curve.
It often takes a lot of experience
to really become very skilled at debugging,
which is why a very practiced programmer has
a great deal of advantage over an inexperienced programmer.
They know the kinds of things to look for, the kinds of tools
to use.
So this is my way of saying, be patient
as you learn the techniques try and figure out
how to debug efficiently.
There are some tools that are provided to you.
First of all, there are some built in tools into the IDEs,
ease into Idle or into Anaconda.
And I encourage you to use them.
You'll see examples of this as you go through some
of the problem sets.
As you hit a bug, you can use the things
that are printed out by the environment
to help you isolate where the error actually occurred.
I know an obvious instinct is, you run a piece of code,
it crashes in the environment.
You instantly go to the code.
Stop, take a look at what was printed out on the screen,
it will tell you something about where it was in the code
when it hit the problem.
It will tell you something about the kind of error
that occurred, and that's valuable to you.
Obviously, use the tutor to help you understand this.
But the third one is again, one of those very simple things,
but something that really practiced programmers
use all the time, and that's the print statement.
Insert statements at different points in your code
that will print out, here's what I'm expecting,
here's what I'm seeing.
That's going to help you isolate where
the code may be going wrong.
It's going to help you narrow into the particular place
in the code that you want to search to find the bug.
And finally, be systematic in your search for a bug.
Treat it like a scientific experiment.
Formulate a hypothesis as to where
you think the bug is occurring, what an experiment would
be to test that, and then run the experiment
to see if it validates or invalidates your hypothesis,
and then move on.
The print statement, as I said, is a great way
to test hypotheses.
And here are some suggestions.
Print when you enter a function.
Print out what the values of the parameters
are to make sure that they are what you expect.
Print the parameters themselves.
At the end, print out the result.
Even if you're going to pass it on to some other function,
print it out so you can see what was
returned to check whether it was what you expect it or not.
Another way to use print statements
we're going to do in a second, which
is to use the bisection method, that is put it print statement
halfway through the code saying, here's what I expected
the state of the computation to be at this point, and here's
what it actually is.
Given that, it's going to help you
narrow into where the bug may occur,
because if you get halfway through the code,
and it's correct, the bug must happen after that.
And you can put in another print statement and keep doing that.
And so that lets you very quickly
isolate which procedure, which function
may be causing the bug to occur.
Those error messages are often really easy to use.
If I get an index error, it tells me
that I'm trying to access something
in a structure that's outside of the length of that structure.
So here's an example that could lead to that,
but more importantly, an index error
tells me, check the bounds of what
I'm using as indices to look at structures.
If I get a type error, it suggests things like,
I'm trying to convert something to a type
that I can't, or I'm trying to use a function on something
whose type does not support that kind of usage.
If I get a name error, it's likely
that I'm trying to reference a nonexistent variable.
I haven't defined or bound the variable initially.
I'm trying to use this value before I've ever created it.
Here's another kind of type error that I might see.
I'm mixing data types together without appropriate coercion.
I'm trying to divide a string by an integer,
rather than casting that string into an int
before I deal with that.
A syntax error, that's something that will often
occur when I do things like forget
to close a parentheses or a quotation.
Here, I'm missing a close paren right there.
And so this is not a well-formed expression,
because I'm trying to combine a print statement with doing
a length call on a structure.
So let the error messages actually
guide what you're looking for in terms of the bug.
Logic errors are harder.
This is where I actually get a value out,
but it's not what I was expecting.
And so what I would suggest here is a couple of things.
First, think before you start writing new code.
An obvious statement, but a valuable thing to do.
Draw some pictures.
Sketch out what you were asking the code to do.
And then take a break, walk away from it, come back
and look at the pictures to say, does my code actually
do what I was thinking it did?
And then one of the best ones, explain your code.
Explain what you were trying to do.
Now, you could explain it to somebody else,
It doesn't matter whether they actually understand it or not,
just explaining it as a process will help you out.
And there's a classic version of this in computer science,
explain it to a rubber ducky.
Walking through the explanation, it
will often help you go, oh, why was I doing that?
I was trying to do this different thing.
But don't just read the code to see if I can find it,
walk through the explanation.
So I advise you all to go out and buy your own rubber ducky,
and have it handy when you try to debug your code.
A great way to drive yourself into doing the explanation
and helping spot where those errors may be occurring.
When you're ready to do the debugging steps,
here are the two obvious things to do.
First, do look at the code.
But ask things like, how did I get the unexpected result?
Don't ask what's wrong, ask, how did I get there?
And is it part of a family of problems
that I might be able to see?
And then finally, do what I suggested earlier.
Use the scientific method.
Study the available data, form a hypothesis
as to what might be causing that particular error to occur.
Come up with an experiment that I can use to test a hypothesis.
And then pick some cases that will actually deal with it
and walk through that cycle.
And do it until you end up with bug-free code.
So don't just write the entire program, test the whole thing,
and then try and debug the whole thing, instead, write a module,
test it, debug it.
Write another module, test it, debug it.
Then test the entire structure, then go back
and do the same cycle here of, test each of the modulus
before you go through the entire integration testing routine.
And similarly, don't change the code,
figure I'll remember where the bug was,
test it, and then either forget where the bug was
or what change you made and go into panic mode.
Instead, back up the code, change it, write down
the potential bug in a comment, test it,
and compare the new version with the old version
to see what was the actual change
and did it catch the piece that I wanted to find.
This latter one I stress, because I see too many people
just go in and start messing with the code,
trying to debug it, and end up with something
even worse than what they had and not able to recover
where they were.
So when you've got code that's buggy,
save away a version of it, take a clean version,
and start modifying it, so that you
can see what were the changes I made that got me to the place
I wanted to get to.