...
So far, we've been talking about how to handle exceptions.
We've seen some nice power to that.
That when Python throws an exception rather than bumping
us up to top level, we can actually say, in this case,
I know what I want to do.
And I can actually write code to handle that exception.
And we saw examples of using that to build little data
structures.
Very nice.
We can actually go the other direction as well, though,
which is we could decide when to raise an exception ourselves.
So rather than returning special values when an error occurs
and then checking to see if that error value was returned,
we could instead say, you know what?
I want to raise an exception when
I'm unable to produce a result consistent with the
specifications of the function.
And for that, we have, not surprisingly, another keyword
called raise.
And the idea is inside of the code,
I can say I want to raise using that keyword an exception.
And I'm going to give the name of the error
that I want to raise in doing that.
It could be an error that's an existing error exception.
It could be one that we're going to create ourselves.
But typically, it's going to be an existing error exception.
So in this case, a value error.
And then, a message that I want to print out.
And typically, that's just a string
that I want to have that tells me what was going on.
Hopefully, something more valuable than just something
is wrong.
It may tell me the specifics that
were happening when I raised this particular exception.
This is now putting me in control
of deciding when to raise an exception
as well as now allowing me to do what
I did in the earlier part of how to handle that exception when
I get there.
Let's look at some examples.
Imagine I want to take a list of two numbers.
And I want to get a ratio of those two lists.
That is, each list I'm going to assume is equal length.
And I'm going to get the ratio of the first element
of the first list, the first element of the second list,
and so on.
And I've got a nice little piece of code here.
It has a form you might expect.
I'm going to set up a list of which I'm
going to record the results.
I'm going to then run down the length of the first list
with a little index going from 0 up to 1
minus the length of the list.
And I'm simply going to try and get
the ratio of those two things and put it
into the thing I'm trying to accumulate.
So I'm running try here.
What I want to do though is deal with a couple
of different cases.
One is, what do I want to have happen
if I get a division by 0?
And in that case, I'm just going to put something in here that's
called not a number.
It's a special thing inside of Python
that I'm going to insert saying, I can't return a number here
because it's infinite.
That's just a standard exception handler.
But when I get anything else, I'm
going to raise a different exception that
tells me I called get ratios with a bad argument.
And then finally, I'm going to try and return the ratios.
Let's see what happens if we actually run this.
So here's an example of get ratios.
I've loaded in.
And let's give it a couple of lists, l1 I'm going to say
is the list 1, 2, 3, 4.
l2 is the list 5, 6, 7, 8.
And my apologies.
I'll do that again. l2 is the list 5, 6, 7, 8.
And if I call get ratios on l1 and l2, it does what I expect.
It gives me those ratios and it ran correctly.
Let's define another list.
Let's make l3 be the list just 5, 6, 7.
If I call get ratios on that with, for example, l1 and l3--
oh, good.
It did what I wanted it to do.
In particular, it threw an error because I'm trying to index
beyond the length of l2.
It's one short of the length of l1.
And notice up here, I'm indexing over the size of l1.
And it did exactly what I wanted.
It raised a value error.
So it did throw me up to top level
because I don't have an exception
handler to deal with that.
But it printed out my information,
not the standard thing that would
have happened if I didn't have a particular handler there.
The last one I want to do is to say, let's let l4 be the list
5, 6, 7, and 0.
And if I do get ratios of l1 and l4, nice.
In this case, the exception handler kicked in.
Because in this case, I have a 0 division error.
And rather than throwing in error,
I said, just substitute in that special symbol, not a number,
in place of the spot where I would have otherwise put it in.
Again, step away from the code for a second.
What we're now showing you is I can certainly handle exceptions
as they come up, but I can also raise
my own kind of error message for different kinds of errors
as they occur.
In this case, when I got a value error giving me out something
specific telling me where I was when this happened.
I can use that to control the flow.
Let's build on that idea and let's look at a second example.
So as I said, we're managing the flow of the program
by raising our own error here.
Let's look at an example where we extend that.
Let's assume we're given a class list for a subject.
And each entry is-- as we did in the earlier part,
it's a list of two things.
A list of the name of the student and a list
of grades on an assignment.
Multiple grades for an assignment.
So I might have a little example here of test grades for Peter
Parker and Bruce Wayne.
And they are both doing pretty well in this class.
What I'd like to do is create a new class list
with a name, grades, and an average.
What's the average that they're doing so far in that?
And you could see the kind of output
I'd like to get here, that Bruce Wayne is doing a little better
than Peter Parker.
OK.
Pick your favorite superhero and which
you want to have do better than somebody else.
How would I do that?
Again, trying to use the idea, which
we're going to do in a second, of using
the exceptions to handle the way we flow through the program.
Here's some code that would do the straightforward
way of doing it.
A little function called get stats.
It takes in a list and what does it do?
It's going to build a new list.
And for each element in that original list,
I'm going to take a list of the first element,
the second element, and an average of the second element.
And I'm assuming I'm inputting things
that have a list of names and a list of grades.
And it's going to compute that out.
An average, of course, just takes that last element,
it adds them up using sum, and divides it
by the length of grades.
And so if I were to do that with a simple, little example,
here I've got an implementation of that.
And I'm going to initially zero out some examples of this
to do a simple version, and then I'm
going to do a slightly more complicated version.
So the simple version is the one that we already have.
And if I run this, and then I look at test grades, which
is where I asked to put the result,
I get what I wanted initially.
Sorry, that's test grades.
And now let's actually run it.
I'm going to do get stats on test grades.
And I get the kind of performance I wanted to get.
Looks good.
OK.
Now, what I want to do, however, is I want to look at a case
where I've got some other entries in here.
So I'm going to rerun this.
I'm going to reload this file.
I've got test grades in.
Here's what test grades looks like.
It's got Captain America with some grades
and it's got Deadpool without any grades entered yet.
And if I do get stats on the test grades-- ah,
I get a division by 0 error.
And that makes sense because in that last entry, length is 0.
I'm trying to divide by 0.
What could I do to deal with that?
Well, as we just said, if I got somebody
where they don't have any grades,
I get that error because I tried to do that division.
Why don't I think about handling it
using this idea of exceptions?
And so in particular, I want to deal with this case.
And here's what I could do.
The first one is I could decide to just notify
the user that something went wrong by putting out a message.
So I'm going to change now average to try to return this.
But if I get a 0 division error, I'm
going to handle it by printing up some data.
And if I go and do that, I'm going to change now
my definition of grades.
Of average, rather.
I'm going to get rid of this version of average.
And I'm going to load that file in.
Now, just make sure I've got the right thing.
There is test grades.
And it's my list.
And if I know say get stats for test grades-- great.
It ran.
Notice what it did, though.
It made a decision.
So first of all, notice on the printout
it printed out no grades data.
So it gave me the warning.
I handled that error by saying that's what I want to do.
But in this case, notice what also happened.
There's the flag for the error, but it substituted in a value.
And the reason it did is because average didn't return anything.
My definition of average doesn't have a return in this case.
And as a consequence, the call to average
gives back that special thing, the none type.
And it inserted none in that spot in the pool.
Maybe I'd like to say that that's
the average for Deadpool, but that
doesn't make a lot of sense.
How could I handle that?
Well, I could decide I'm just going to give
a student with no grades a 0.
Seems like a reasonable thing to do.
And now I can change my handler.
Again, catching that 0 division error idea,
but putting in an explicit return.
This says not only do I want to print out
a note that says something didn't go the way I expected it
to, but let me give me back a value that I can run on it.
So now, let's go and see what happens when we do that.
So I'm going to remove this version of average
and replace it with one that has that return inside of it.
And when I call this, again, let's check and see
we're in the right place.
Let's make sure that test grades was loaded properly.
And it was.
And if I now do get stats on test grades-- oh, good.
Deadpool now has a 0.
Doesn't say how bad or good Deadpool is,
he just didn't turn any quizzes and he has no grades.
And so now what we see here is we still flag the error,
but we've changed what gets returned to insert something
that makes more sense for the data structure
I'm trying to build.
And so we can see we can use our own ability to raise errors,
But to handle errors, to deal with things in a manner
that we want, rather than simply stopping execution and pumping
it back up to the user to try and decide
how to handle all of that.