...
Now that I've started building a hierarchy,
one of the things I'd like to show you
is how that modularity, that associating methods
with different data attributes around a particular class,
makes it easy for me to change behaviors for one class
without changing behaviors elsewhere.
And to do that, I'm going to add in one more kind of object
to my hierarchy-- a Professor, also a kind of MIT
Person, but behaves differently, as you've probably
already seen.
And I'm going to use this, as I said,
as an example to see how one can leverage methods
from other classes in the hierarchy
but use that modularity to isolate changes to methods when
I want to.
Let's start by defining a Professor.
Again, it inherits, as a kind of MIT Person,
I'm going to have an initialization method,
as before.
And as I did with students, I'm going
to inherit or use the inherited MIT Person initialization
method to set it up.
But I'll add in one more attribute-- the department
in which this Person is a Professor.
This Professor can speak.
Again, I'm going to use the underlying MIT Person speak()
method.
But I'm going to add in a few other things to the utterance.
And you can see the example here.
I'm going to, in fact, say what department the Person is in
and how they say things.
And we'll see an example in a second.
Professors not only speak, they lecture.
And so I'll give the Professor the ability to lecture.
And notice here I'm going to use my own speak() method,
or the Professor speak() method, to the lecture() by adding some
other pieces in.
So this method will shadow the MIT Person speak() method
for professors, although it will use that inherited speak()
method.
And lecture() will use the base speak() method associated with
the Professor but add other things in as we do it.
Let's see what happens if we were to do this.
So I'm going to go back to the things I've already built,
some of my early examples, and just look at how the different
speak() methods work.
So I've got an MIT Person, and I can do that.
I can say, I'm going to print out
asking M1 to speak and just say a very simple "Hi there."
And it prints out, as we saw before, "Gates says,
'Hi there,'" because that's the speak() method for an MIT
Person.
Now I know that that uses that base method.
Let's look at another example.
I'm going to print out for a Student.
And if I do print s1 speak-- again, just saying "Hi there,"
it prints out, "Damon says, 'Dude, hi there.'" It's using
the Undergraduate speak() method because that was the kind
of Student we had created, which uses the MIT Person method
but simply adds "Dude" to the front of the utterance.
What else might I do?
Well, let's have a Faculty Member.
And I've created a Faculty Member here.
Let's just have a Faculty Member speak.
And if we ask that Faculty Member to say "Hi there"-- I
should have said earlier, the Faculty Member I created
was a Professor named Dr. Arrogant in Course 6.
And he prints out, "In Course 6, we say,
'Hi there.'" And this is coming from the change I made to that
speak() method for a Faculty Member.
And finally, if I were to have a Faculty Member lecture--
so I asked this Faculty Member that I created to lecture
on the topic of "Hi there"-- he says-- or rather,
it prints out, "Arrogant says, 'In Course 6, we say,
"It is obvious that-- Hi there."'" So notice what
the lecture() method does.
It uses the Professor speak() method,
which incorporated that "In Course 6, we say,"
but it added into it as part of the utterance this little
annoying phrase, "It is obvious that."
Key point-- each class has a speak() method.
And in the hierarchy, we start with the class instance
or the class of which we have an instance,
use that speak() method.
We may inherit from higher up in the hierarchy.
But we have all of those pieces nicely
contained to the instances, so speaking
different kinds of objects do in a different way.
With that in mind, we could make some changes.
So in particular, because I've got that isolation,
I could go into the MIT Person speak() method and change how
we have this actually print out.
In particular, I'm going to have it return the name rather than
just the last name as part of that says() method.
Let's see what would happen if I did that.
So I have a version of my file over here that does that.
And if I now change that in the Person method--
I'm going to reload that file-- and in particular,
if I were to go through the same instances,
now the print() methods, notice, all at in front the full name.
Why?
Because all of these methods use the underlying MIT Person
speak() method.
They just added other pieces into it.
In the case of a Student, it added in "Dude."
In the case of a Faculty Member, it added in "In Course 6,
we say."
In the case of lecturing, it added in other pieces.
But in all cases, ultimately, it calls the underlying MIT Person
method.
So all of these classes inherit that.
But I could make a different kind of change.
For example, I could decide that I'm going to change
the Undergraduate Student's speak() method to, rather than
saying "Dude," say "Yo, bro."
And if I were to make that change
and come back and try it, I load it into my machine,
and I were to print those things out,
I would get the following behavior.
It looks exactly like the previous case.
The only difference is right there,
that the Undergraduate speak() method uses "Yo, bro."
Notice it doesn't change Faculty Member either speaking
or lecturing, it doesn't change the MIT Person,
and for two different reasons.
For the MIT Person case, Undergraduate
is lower in the hierarchy, so in fact it
would not have a change there.
In the case of a Faculty Member, it's
in another place in the hierarchy,
and it does not use the Student's method,
it uses the MIT Person's method.
I've modularized it.
I've captured a behavior locally.
And that's really nice.