...
OK.
Let's get concrete about this.
Let's look at the specifics of how we both define a class,
and then implement instances of that class.
So, if we want to define our own type,
we're going to start by using the keyword class,
not surprisingly.
And that's going to tell us we're
about to create the definition of a new class.
So we're going to start with the class definition.
We're going to give it a name.
In this case, I'm creating a coordinate.
That's simply an x-y pairing of points in the plane.
And then each class definition is
going to take one argument, which is the parent class.
And initially, we're going to create
classes that inherit from the underlying object
class of Python.
So we'll always just have object here.
When we start building hierarchies
we'll see that we want to extend that idea.
But just to repeat it, I've got a class definition
I've got a name, in this case, coordinate.
And its parent in this case is object.
It's followed as always by a colon to tell me
I'm done with this.
And then immediately below that, I'm
going to define the attributes of this class.
And I'm going to have them indented, as always, to tell me
where the bounds of that class definition lie.
Now, the word object means the coordinate is itself
a kind of Python object.
And that means, it's going to inherit
all of the attributes of the underlying Python object.
We'll come back to that in a second,
but that's going to be valuable.
One last piece of nomenclature-- we
say that a coordinate is a subclass of an object,
and an object is a superclass of a coordinate.
We're going to have a subclass inherit from its parent
or superclass object.
So, simple start, define a class with a name in an object.
Now I have to get into, how do I actually put attributes inside
of that class definition?
So first of all, what are the attributes?
Well, they're going to be data and procedures that
belong to this class.
If I take my example of a coordinate,
a coordinate's got an x and a y value.
So I'm going to have some data attributes that
are the x and y values that are associated with a coordinate.
What I want to do is think about those data attributes
and as other objects that make up the class-- things that
get inherently glued together and can be treated as a unit.
A point in the plane is a unit-- it
happens to have pieces in it.
But I want to have that class capture those things together.
So as an example, while a coordinate is made up
of two numbers, a coordinate itself
is something that I can use.
Those are the data attributes.
We also need ways to use the data.
And those are what we call the procedural attributes
or the methods.
Think of methods as functions that work only for this class.
So for example, if I want to compute
the distance between two coordinates, I could do that,
and I can do that in a second to find a distance method
associated with coordinates.
But it doesn't typically makes sense
to think about doing distances between strings
or distances between lists.
I'm going to create a method that
belongs only to this class.
And it's going to be seated inside of that class
as one of the data-- sorry, one of the procedural attributes
associated with the class.
OK.
So how do I do that?
Well, first thing I've got to do is
define how I actually create instances of this object.
And for that, we use a special method called init.
And in fact it's written a very special way.
It has got two underscores, the word init, and then
two underscores.
We're always going to do it that way.
It's a special method.
And this special method is going to create an instance
when I actually use coordinate as a call.
Now, what's inside of init?
Its first argument is a parameter
that's going to refer to an instance of the class.
And by tradition, we always call it, "self."
In fact, you'll notice when you type it in,
the Python environment always types, "self"
in a different color and in a different,
in this case italic font, to distinguish that it refers
to an instance of the clash.
We also want to give this thing that's
going to create instances the initial data.
If a coordinate has an x and y value,
I want my creation of an instance
to take in a value for x and a value in y.
And we're going to glue them together.
And the way we glue them together is we're
going to actually create bindings for the names
x and y to the values passed in.
And what you can do is think of this
as, when we actually invoke the creation of an instance-- which
we're going to do in a second-- this
will bind the variables x and y within that instance
to the supplied values.
I'm going to come back in a second to why it
says self dot x and self dot y.
But think of this as saying, within that instance
to which self refers, I'm binding x and y to
the values passed in.
This is typically the first method
that we have inside of a class definition.
Because we have to say, how am I going
to create instances of this class?
This is also inherently defining the data attributes
associated with this particular class, an x and a y value.
OK.
Let's make a couple of versions of this.
So I'm actually going to do that.
I've got over here, on my machine,
a definition of coordinate.
And I can now create an instance.
I can say, I'm going to let c be a coordinate.
So I simply use the name coordinate.
Oh, and that's nice.
Notice when I did the open print--
I'm going to do it again before it disappears--
it tells me what the arguments are that are expected.
And I'm going to give it two, an x and a y value-- 3 and 4.
I'm going to define origin to be the origin
of my coordinate system.
So it is another coordinate of 0 and 0.
And notice, each time I invoke coordinate,
the name of a class, it's creating a new instance.
What it's doing is it's calling that init method,
and using that to create local bindings.
Now, you might notice here that there's no version of self.
Wait a minute.
Didn't I have in my definition, the definition of init
was self x and y?
I did, but the style, or the process if you like, in Python
is that self automatically points
to the particular instance that I've just created.
And Python automatically provides that argument for you.
So when I call init, I only call it with the arguments
that I need to provide in order to create the data attributes.
Once I've got that, I now have instance variables
inside of that class instance.
And I can get to them.
So for example, I could say, print out the x-value value
associated with c.
And there it is, 3.
Or I can print, the x-value associated with the origin.
And there it is.
I just printed it out.
Think of this as c giving me an instance.
It did, because I created it.
And now I'm going to try and get the x thing associated with c.
So, I create a new instance of an object.
I pass in the arguments.
I use the dot notation to access an attribute of an instance.
And what I want to think about is,
what does it mean to do that actual accessing?
As I already said, notice that the argument for self
is automatically supplied by Python.
So I don't need to provide it.
The way to think about this is as follows.
Think of c, an instance I created with coordinate--
think of it as pointing to a frame.
You may remember we saw that when we did function calls.
That every time we called a function,
we created a new frame.
In essence, a class definition is doing that as well.
Coordinate is creating a new frame associated with c.
Within the scope of that frame, we bound values
to data attribute variables.
So inside of c, there is a binding
for x and a binding for y, to 3 and 4 respectively.
C dot x is then interpreted as saying the following.
Get the value of c.
Oh, that's a frame.
And then inside of that frame, look up
the value associated with x.
So c dot x says, get the value of c.
That's a frame.
Now I'll use the next thing to say,
what's the binding for x inside of that frame.
And thus, that's going to make it easier
to understand why c dot x gives me back 3,
and origin dot x gives me back 0.
In each case, they're referring to a different frame in which
the variable x is bound.
And just like with functions, there
was no confusion about which binding to use.
The same thing with different instances
of the same object type.