...
Now that we've seen the basic idea of creating a class
and creating instances of a class,
and we've seen the idea of defining methods
for them, including methods that are sort of the built in
or associated methods-- like what does it print like,
how do I create an instance-- let's look
at how we would use this idea of a class.
And probably the best way to do that is
to simply take an example.
So I'm going to create a new type of object
to represent a number as a fraction, and literally
as a fraction, not as the floating point
equivalent of that.
What do I need?
I need to say what's the internal representation?
What are the data attributes I want to glue together
and how am I going to represent them?
And then what's the interface, or if you
like, the methods that I'm going to use
to interact with instances of those Fraction objects?
In my case for a fraction, I want
a numerator and a denominator, a top part and a bottom part.
In terms of the interaction, the interface, the methods,
I certainly want a print representation
so I don't get something messy coming out.
But I'd like to think about simple things
like how do I add fractions, how do I subtract fractions.
And one other thing I might like is, if I wanted to,
how do I convert a fraction into an actual floating point number
that I could then use standard Python arithmetic
operations on?
Let's see how we would build that.
And what you're going to see here
is less the details of doing fractions, more
the idea of how I use the methods to define behaviors
that I want to associate with different objects,
in this case, fractions.
OK, so initially, I need to define the class of a Fraction.
I use class to say it's the definition of class.
I got the name.
And as before, this is going to inherit from the underlying
object class.
I also need, as always, to define
what does it mean to create one of these objects.
So I've got an init method.
It takes in two arguments besides self.
That is a numerator and a denominator.
And I'm just going to bind those locally
within the frame associated with every instance of a class.
I also want to define what I want to have printed out
when I do this.
And here I'm simply going to have it print out
a string representation of the numerator
and the denominator separated by a slash,
sort of like you'd expect to see inside of a fraction.
There is my definition initially of what a fraction looks like.
Let's see what happens if I use that.
So I'm going to go over to my machine and load this up.
And let's do the two definitions.
Let's give the name one_half to the fraction of 1 and 2.
Let's give the name two_thirds to the fraction, obviously,
of 2 and 3.
And let's see if it prints out appropriately.
So I print out one_half.
Yep, does what I'd like.
And obviously you would expect two_thirds
ought to do the same thing, but let's just check it.
There we go.
All right, so we can create fractions.
We're can create a bunch of them, a little boring.
What could we do with fractions?
Well as I said, I want to do some operations on it.
But before I do that, I want to introduce one more
important idea.
And that goes back to something we
talked about earlier, which I'm going to pull in in a second.
And the new idea is to create something that
lets me access data attributes.
These are often called getters.
I'm going to get out the elements of that.
And here I'm going to define a getter for numerator
and a getter for denominator.
I'm going to give them obvious names.
I could give them anything.
But I'm going to say get_numer should give me back
the numerator of a fraction.
And get_denom should give me back the value
of the denominator of an instance of a fraction.
Why am I creating those?
Well those are going to be important
because it's going to separate out
accessing the internal representation
from the actual use of the representation.
But let's check to make sure it does the right thing.
You can see what I can expect it to do.
And if I say get half-- sorry, one_half,
and I use get_numer, that's great.
It gives me back the numerator of one_half.
Notice the call.
There's the dot.
And I'm going to step through this carefully. one_half points
to an instance.
It's a frame somewhere.
The dot says, get the binding for get_numer in that frame.
Oh yeah, that was the definition that I did right back here
of a method inside-- actually the frame of coordinate--
sorry, frame of fraction.
But I inherit it because one_half
is an instance of Fraction.
But the last piece is that simply gives you
back the procedure.
To make it run, I have to invoke it.
And while it takes no arguments other than self, which
is automatically provided, I need to say open, close paren
to actually invoke it.
Do the same thing with get denominator.
I can get out the pieces of them.
As we said, this is a procedure.
I've got to invoke it.
And remember again, self is provided separately for me.
I can now use that to define things
like how do I add fractions or how do I subtract fractions.
And notice that while it looks a little messy at code,
it actually is going to have an important property.
So here is the definition of add.
It takes two arguments, the instance itself,
and some other fraction.
And inside of there I'm just going
to do the work to actually define what it means
to add together two fractions.
I take the numerator of one, the denominator of the other,
multiply them together.
Take the denominator of one, the numerator of the other,
multiply them together, add those up.
That's the new numerator.
The denominator is just the product of those two products.
And if you look at the slide carefully,
I notice I have some typos here.
Ignore them.
My method is actually going to do them correctly.
That snuck in somehow into my slide.
Last piece of this is, having computed that numerator
and denominator, I need to return an instance.
And I create one by calling Fraction
with new values for the numerator and the denominator.
Subtraction does the same kind of thing.
Let's see what happens if I actually use that.
So I've got those two versions there.
Let's call new what I get by taking one_half and two_thirds
and adding them together.
And what does new look like-- perfect.
Let's do one more example.
Let's call three_quarters the obvious thing,
the fraction of 3 and 4.
Let's just make sure it works in other kinds of versions here.
So I'm going to call second new.
Well actually let's just print out three_quarters.
I can print it.
And there it is.
And if I let second_new be, let's
do two_thirds minus three_quarters,
because I defined sub as well.
Needs to type it properly.
My apologies, let's do it one more time.
This is two_thirds minus three_quarters.
I can print that out.
Oh great, exactly what I'd expect.
I've now got the ability to create
new instances of Fractions by doing
arithmetic operations on them.
And notice how plus and minus are overriding,
if you like, the built in versions of those.
And I'm using that in order to be
able to do this in a manner that lets me type things that
make sense, but have things come out the right way.
Last thing I said I wanted to do is
to be able to convert fractions into floats.
And that's easy.
convert would simply take the numerator,
by using the getter for that, take the denominator
by using the getter for that, and just do division.
And so if I ask, for example, to convert second_new-- ah,
I did that wrong.
My apologies.
I'm going to do second_new.convert().
It prints out the floating point representation of those pieces.
Great, it's exactly what I'd like to have.
There are some examples of that, just like we did.
And this is something that's going to give us the ability
now to think about elements of this class and simply use them.
I'm going to do one more example.
But before I do, I want to say another word
about those getters and setters.
Why do I want to create separate getters and setters?
Remember, we said we don't want to directly manipulate
the internal representation of an object.
We'd like to separate the use of the object
from what's inside of it.
And those getters and setters nicely do that.
It says any time I want to access something
inside an object, let me use the method that gets
that part of the object out.
I'm going to come back to that idea
when we do our second example.
And the second example is, suppose we wanted to build
a little collection, a set of integers.
Initially the set's empty.
And I want to have the property of that
set be that an integer appears only once inside the set.
That's what we would call a representational invariant
of this particular object.
And I'm going to enforce that by the way I write the code.
I don't want to have to go and check,
do I have more than one instance inside the object?
I want it to be the case that as I add elements to this set,
I'm always making sure that there's never
more than one particular version of that integer
inside of that set.
I need two pieces.
Data representation, I'm just going
to use a list to store the elements of the set.
And I need an interface.
How do I interact with this?
And for that I'm going to have the ability
to insert an element, the ability
to check if an element is there, and the ability
to remove an element.
And the description is exactly what you'd expect.
insert's going to put that element into the set
if it's not already there.
member will tell me true if in fact an element's
inside the set.
And remove will take the element out of the set
and complain if I try to take something out that wasn't
already inside of the set.
Again, a bunch of words.
Let's do an example.
Here's the definition of the IntegerSet class.
And I'm going to do this a little more quickly because you
should be getting used to these pieces.
I have something that creates instances.
In this case, there is no argument to it other than self
because it starts out as empty, and it's simply
creating an internal binding for the variable vals, which
is going to be in my internal name for the set,
to the empty list.
I can insert things into the set.
And here's where I'm going to enforce
the representational invariant.
I'm going to take advantage of the property of lists.
So when I want to insert a particular element
into an instance of an IntegerSet,
I'm going to first say, is that element inside the list?
And I'm just using that iterable operation on this to use that.
If it isn't, I'm going to append it into the list.
If it is, I'm simply going to skip by because there's
nothing to do.
I want to check if something's inside the list.
Again, I can use the property of a list.
I can simply say, return e in self.vals.
That simply says if e is in that set, that list,
it's going to be true, otherwise false.
What else did I need?
I need to be able to remove an element from a set.
And here I'm going to use that nice property of exceptions.
I'm going to try to simply remove, directly,
something from a list.
I'm using the property of list here, because vals is a list.
Remove is a method associated with list.
And it's going to try to remove the first instance-- should
be the only instance-- the first instance of that variable
e from that list.
If in fact e was not in the list,
it's going to raise an error.
And the exception then is going to come down to here,
and I'm going to raise my own particular error to say,
that particular element was not found.
I'm going to override the underlying ValueError exception
method.
And finally, I'm going to use string
to define how I want to print out the elements of a set.
This is a little funky, but what I'm simply going to do
is take vals, which is a list, and I'm
going to sort it by using the sort method and call it.
And notice I've got three dots here.
It actually makes sense.
It says self gives me the instance.
Dot says look up vals inside of that instance, which
is simply a binding.
And then because vals is a list, the next dot, this one,
says find the method sort associated with lists,
and then apply it by calling it right there.
Once I've sorted it, I'm going to run
through a little loop, where I set result
to be the empty string.
And then for each element in the now sorted version of vals,
I'm going to simply add it in together with a comma.
And then when I'm ready to return it,
I'm going to return a string that has
a curly bracket on each end.
And I got one extra comma hanging around
at the end of the last element.
So I'm going to take result and return everything
but that last element to get rid of that last piece.
And now let's try it out.
I'll show you some examples here,
but I actually want to go over and type them on the machine
so you can see that it does what we would expect.
So I'm going to define s to be an integer set.
And I could print out what s it is,
and it just gives me the two curly braces.
There's nothing there.
Now let's put some pieces inside of s.
I'm going to insert 3 into s.
I'm going to insert 4 into that set.
I'm going to insert 3 again, because I have a short memory
and I've forgotten I've already done that.
And I want to say oh, wait a minute, what does s look like?
Oh, that's nice.
It's just got one version of 3 plus 4.
I go back to what I said earlier.
I'm going to enforce in my implementation
that representational invariant, that an element appears
only once.
And if you look back at the code,
you realize that second insert of 3
would have checked to see is 3 already
in the internal representation?
It is, so I don't add it.
What else could I do?
Well, I could check to see if something's in the list.
So I could say is 3 in the set?
Yes, yes it is.
Is 6 in the set?
Yes, no it isn't.
And that's great.
Notice by the way, on my machine,
whenever I type one of those methods,
it nicely brings up something that tells me
what the docstring associated with it
is, what it expects to do, what are the inputs it's expecting
there, things that are going to help us think about what
do these different methods do.
What else could I do?
I can remove something.
So I can go back to s and say, let's remove 3.
And that did that fine.
And let's get rid of-- sorry, let's add in 6 to that.
And if I look at what s now consists of,
not surprisingly, I've taken out the 3.
I've added in the 6.
I'm simply using those built in methods to manipulate that set.
I could do one other thing here.
And I'm not going to do it on my machine
but simply point out what will happen here.
If I try to remove an element that's not currently
in that instance of the set, it's going to throw an error.
And it's going to print out what I asked it to print out,
which is different from this, the generic exception
that I would raise, because I raised
a specific version of ValueError that said, please print out
that the specific element in the string
not found, telling me what it was that went wrong
when I tried to do all of this.
So there are two examples.
Notice how we define an init method for each of them.
We define a string method for each of them
to tell us how we're going to print things out.
And then I create methods specific to this kind of class
that will let me manipulate instances of that class.