...
So we've seen some quadratic complexity sorting
algorithms-- OK, but not great.
And clearly we'd like to get the sort as efficient as possible.
And fortunately, we already know an idea
that we can use to do that, and that's
to use divide and conquer.
If I could somehow break the problem down
into half size chunks and do work on that,
that would be really great.
And that leads to a great technique called merge sort,
a very common sorting algorithm.
And here is the basic idea of merge sort.
If I got a list of length 0, or length 1, it's already sorted.
I'm done.
If I have a list longer than that,
let's just split the list into 2 parts of roughly equal size,
and sort each of them.
Once I've got them sorted, I'm going to merge them together.
And I'm going to do that, as we'll
see in an example in a second, by taking advantage of the fact
that if I have 2 sorted lists, I can just
look at the first element of each, ask which one is smaller,
and put it into the result, and then
look at the next portion of it.
That's going to be a nice linear time solution.
And so when I do that, once I've got to an empty one of those 2
lists, I just copy the rest of the list, and I'm done.
You can see the idea.
Break it down into smaller and smaller and smaller
sized problems, until I get to something
that's trivially sorted.
And then I'm going to merge those results,
and keep merging those results out, taking advantage
of the fact I'm splitting the problem in half at each stage.
Let's look at a visualization of that to get a sense of that.
Again, it's a nice divide and conquer idea.
So if I've got a big list that's unsorted,
I'm going to split it into half.
If those are still too big and they're unsorted,
I'll keep splitting until I get down to something
where I've just got lists of one element.
Once I'm down at that level, merging
is actually really easy.
I just look at the 2 and decide which one is smaller.
And that gives me lists of size 2 that are sorted.
But now merging those is also pretty easy,
as we'll see in a second, because I'd simply
look at each of the elements in the 2 lists,
putting the smallest one in.
And I merge those.
And then I merge those.
And then I merge those, until I get back to something
that is overall sorted.
Nice divide and conquer algorithm.
Should have a nice complexity.
We're going to look at that in a second.
Before we do, let's again get Professor Guttag
and a set of MIT students to give you
a little visual demonstration of doing merge sort.
And then we'll come back and look
at what's the actual complexity of the algorithm.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
So we're about to demonstrate a merge sort.
And we're going to sort this rather Motley collection of MIT
students by height.
So the first thing we need to do is
we're going to ask everyone to split into a group of two.
So you split a little bit.
You two are together.
You two are together, and you are all by yourself.
I'm sorry.
All right, so now let's take the first group.
Take a step down.
And what we do is we sort this group by height,
with the shortest on the left.
And look at this, we don't have to do anything.
Thank you.
Feel free to go back up.
We then sort the next pair, please.
And it looks to me like we need to switch.
All right, take a step back.
Ladies, OK.
Ladies, gentleman, also OK.
And again, OK.
And I think you're in the correct order.
Now what we do is we take these groups and merge the groups.
So let's have these two-- going to sort these groups,
have them step forward.
And now what we're doing is we're
doing a merge of the two sorted groups.
So we start by merging them.
We'll take the leftmost person in this group
and compare her to the first person in this group,
and decide she's still the shortest.
Take a step back.
Now we're going to look at you and say,
you're actually taller than this fellow.
So you now step up there.
And we're good here.
Both of you take a step back.
Now we'll take these two groups and follow the same procedure.
We'll merge them.
Let's see, we'll compare you, the first person in this group,
to the first person in this group.
Now it's a little tricky.
So let's see, the two of you compare.
Let's see, back to back.
We have a winner.
Step back.
And now we need to compare the shortest person in this group
to the shortest person in this group.
We have a winner.
It's you.
I'm sorry.
And now we're OK.
Please step back.
Now we'll have these two groups come forward.
We'll compare the shortest person in this group
to the shortest person in that group.
I actually need you guys to get back to back here.
You are the winner.
And it's pretty clear that the shortest person in this group
is shorter than the shortest person in that group.
So you go there and you step back.
And now we repeat the same process.
And you can see that we have a group of students
sorted in order by height.
[CLAPPING]
[END VIDEO PLAYBACK]
So again, that visualization is, as we just
saw with the students, pretty straightforward.
I'm going to do sub pieces and sort them and then merge them.
And as you see with the visualization
of this algorithm, it starts with smaller pieces,
does a merge sort on those smaller pieces,
and keeps doing that until it can do a merge sort
on the entire element.
And you can also see, even if I get to 2 sublists of 1/2
the size of the problem, the merge
is pretty straightforward to do.
And that's what's going to give us
the power of having a nice complexity to this algorithm.
So let's look at the merging part.
And then we'll look at the subdivision part.
The idea here is if I've got two lists that are sorted,
I want to simply say, look at the first element in each,
that comparison, and put it into the result.
The smallest one goes in.
Having done that, one of the lists is now smaller.
And again, I'm going to look at the first element of each.
In this case, the 2 is going to go into the result,
and the second list has gotten smaller.
And I'll simply keep doing that simple comparison
of the first element of each list, putting the smaller
one into my result, until I get to a stage
where one of the lists is empty, at which case
I simply copy the remainder of the list that's not
empty to the end of the list.
And I'm done.
You can see I might have to take a linear number of steps
in the size of the lists to be able to get to that stage.
But that's still not bad.
And that's going to be nice, because, in many cases,
it will actually be faster if I actually
don't have to look at all the remaining elements of a list.
So merging is going to be pretty straightforward.
So here's the code that would do it.
Merging simply says, given a left and right sublist
that we know are sorted, what am I going to do?
I'm going to set up a result into which I'm
going to store the values.
And I'm going to set up a couple of indices, i and j.
And basically, I'm going to let them walk down the list.
So again, I'm not making copies of the list.
I'm simply looking at the elements.
As long as i is not to the end of the length
of the left sublist, and j is not
to the end of the length of the right sublist,
I'm going to do the comparison.
And if the left one is smaller, I'm
going to add that element into the result.
Again, I know append is constant.
So that's nice.
And I change i, just as I did in my example.
I now move my index in the left list up by 1.
On the other hand, if the right element is smaller,
I add it in, and I change j.
And I'll keep doing that until one of the lists is exhausted.
And then these two cases simply tell
me, in either of those cases, just add
in the remainder of that list.
Great.
What do I know here?
I've got left to right sublists that are ordered.
So I'm just moving the indices for the sublists.
It's avoiding that copy of the list.
And so that cost is basically going
to be linear in the size of the list.
When the right sublist is empty, I
copy the rest of the left sublist.
When the left sublist is empty, I
copy the remaining elements in the right sublist.
And then I just return the result.
What's the complexity here?
I go through two lists, but only one pass.
And I'm only comparing the smallest elements
in each sublist.
So the complexity is basically order of the length of the left
and the length of the right sublist.
Overall, I've got order length of the longer list comparisons,
and so this is always going to be linear
in the length of the lists.
So the merge stage is linear, depending
on how long those lists are.
OK, now how do I put it together?
Knowing I know how to merge, I do
the following for merge sort.
Given a list, I say, if there's only 0 or 1 elements there,
I'm done.
Just return a copy of the list and I'm all set.
Otherwise, there is that nice pattern.
Find the midpoint.
Break this in half.
Find the midpoint by taking the length of the list,
doing an integer divide by 2.
And then simply do a merge sort on half of the list-- that's
the smaller half of the list-- do a merge sort
on the left side of the list, then
the right side of the list.
Once I get those back, simply merge them together,
and I'm done.
So what I'm doing here is treating base case,
dividing the problem in half, solving two sub problems,
and then conquering it with the merge step
to bring it back down-- nice, crisp, elegant solution.
What else do we want to know here?
Well, let's just look at an example
of how we would do this, and then
look at the overall complexity.
So imagine I have a list of 8 elements, as you see up here.
I'm initially going to break them in half,
and I need to go off and do a merge sort of the left half.
Again, I break it in half.
I need to do a merge sort to the left half.
And eventually I get down to actually 2 base cases.
The first base case, the solution I can just pass back,
simply list of one element.
Same thing with the second one.
And I just am doing that merge.
And that gets passed up to the place I wanted to do it.
I do the same thing with the right 1/2, same kind of merge.
That gets passed.
And now I can merge 4 and 8, and 1 and 6
with that simple little linear search
to get out the solution I would like.
Halfway there.
Same thing on the other 1/2.
Having passed that back, I can go to the other half
and very quickly get it down to a base case.
Merge those results.
Get it down to another base case.
Those 2 get back up and get merged into an unordered list.
And now I can simply merge those 2 sublists
to get out the overall sorted list I wanted.
I show you this diagram because you
can see that a nice pattern.
This is breaking it down in a nice way
into smaller pieces of things.
And you already ought to have a good sense
of what's the complexity here.
The complexity of the overall breaking down into sub pieces
is going to be probably-- and we'll
see in a second-- logarithmic, because I'm
reducing the size of the problem in 1/2 at each point.
The wrinkle here is that the merge we saw
was linear in the size of the problem.
So let's put those two pieces together.
At the first level of recursion, I've
got n over 2 elements in each list.
And so I've got order n plus order n, which
by that additive law of complexity is still order n,
in terms of solving that problem.
Meaning, once I've got the solution,
I've got to do basically linear amount of work to do the merge.
At the second level, I've got n over 4 elements in each list.
And there are 2 merges there.
We saw that in that diagram.
So while the size of the problem is smaller,
I've got twice as many searches.
And if you think about it, I'm still
at that entire second level looking at each of the elements
probably once.
So it's also order n.
At each recursion level, the merge step is order n.
The size of the list is smaller, but I got more of them.
And that basically cancels out I've got a linear search.
The good news is, how many times do I do it?
I've already hinted at it.
You know the answer.
I'm doing a logarithmic number of steps.
Because I'm basically saying, given a problem of size n,
a 1 recursive call is n over 2.
2 recursive calls is n over 4.
At k recursive calls is order n to the k.
I'm done when end n to the k is of size 1.
That's when k is log in.
And this is an example of something
I promised to you earlier, it's order n log n.
Its log linear.
So it's not quite as nice as logarithmic.
It's not quite as nice as linear.
But it's a lot better than quadratic, or certainly
than exponential.
And this is a characteristic of a wide class of problems
that are really nice.
n log n, log linear, great solution.
So what do I have for sorting?
I can be dumb about it and use bogosearch.
Good luck.
I could use bubble sort.
I could the use selection sort.
They both have a similar property
that they are a quadratic in size.
Timing wise, selection sort is probably a little bit faster.
One of the advantages of selection sort
is that I can guarantee that the first i elements are sorted.
So in fact, if I want to stop the computation after I
get some number of the best elements out,
I could do that without having to sort the rest of the list.
And that's better than doing bubble sort.
But my best option is merge sort.
And in fact, while we won't do it here,
one can show that n log n is the fastest time in which one
can actually do a sort.
But having an n end log n sort time
is nice, because if I amortize that cost over searching,
I actually have something that's going to work out quite nicely.
And so now you've seen search.
You've seen sort.
And you've seen a wonderful example
of an elegant class of complexity, which are
those log linear algorithms.