...
We've seen some simple classes of algorithms, constant, log,
linear.
And we didn't do log linear.
But we'll do that one in a little while.
The next class are polynomial complexity.
And the most common here are quadratic.
The complexity grows with the square
of the size of the input.
Again, I want you to see what are some of the characteristics
to lead to that kind of algorithm.
And one of the things we're going to see here
is that this commonly occurs when
we have nested loops or recursive function calls inside
of the algorithm.
And we need to say that in a way where the recursive function
call has some costs other than constant.
Because as we saw with factorial,
you can have recursive function calls
and have it still be linear.
As before, let's look at some examples
and see the characteristics that lead to this kind of behavior.
Here's a simple algorithm.
I want to explain it.
But again, I'm less concerned about what it does.
I'm more interested in showing you
what the pattern is that leads to this.
So this is an algorithm that given two lists of elements--
could be numbers, could be something else-- but given
two lists is going to try to decide
is the first list a subset of the second list, meaning
every element of the first list does it also occur
in the second list even though there
may be other elements inside the second list.
Let's look at the code and the characteristics of the code.
And then let's analyze it.
So this starts by taking an element in the first list.
It's going to set up a little flag here
that initially says I don't yet have a match.
And then given that element from the first list,
it's going to loop over all the elements of the second list
asking do I have an instance of that element
in the second list.
If I find one right here, I'm going to set that flag to true
and break out of that loop.
Once I've broken out of that loop, I then test.
And having set match to true, the if not match doesn't hold.
And so I don't return false.
I go back around to the loop and get the next element
of the first list.
On the other hand, if I go through all of this search
here and don't find a match, then the matched flag
is set to false.
And when I come to this test, I'm
going to break out of the entire thing by returning false.
If I get through the entire set of the list L1
and I've found a match in all cases, in that case,
I'm going to return true.
Now.
You notice here I've got nested loops.
I've got an outer loop on L1.
I've got an inner loop on L2.
And even though I could break out of either of those lists,
either here or here, we know that it's
the worst case behavior that we're interested in.
And that's going to happen when in fact L1
is in fact a subset of L2 because I'm
going to search through all of L1 looking for that solution.
Key thing I want you to do if I step back from this
is to notice here I've got a nested loop, a loop
inside of a loop.
And that's characteristic of quadratic complexity.
And let's see why.
So if I take my code, I can now ask what is the order of growth
here.
First of all, I know that the outer loop is generally
going to be executed the length of L1 times.
So however many elements there are in L1, let's call
that, for example, n, is going to execute that loop n times
because it's going to ask for each element,
does it have a match.
Yes.
It's possible they could stop earlier.
But in the worst case, it's going
to go through all of them.
What else do I know?
I know that for each outer iteration, for each element
in L1 I'm going to go through this inner loop,
this loop up to the length of L2 times.
And in fact, in the worst case, I
am going to go through it up to the length of L2 times.
So what do I have then?
I've got an outer loop.
I do length of L1 times.
For each one of those, I do length
of L2 kinds of operations.
And by our multiplication log we know that that basically
says this order of growth is the product of the length of L1
times the length of L2.
What's the worst case?
The worst case is when they're both of the same length.
And in that case, again, let's just call that n.
We're going to do n squared operations,
n times n operations.
And as I said, the fact that we might break out
of the loop earlier doesn't change the order
of growth of the algorithm.
The worst case is basically quadratic in the length
of the list.
You've seen the characteristic.
Nested loops is a nice characteristic of something
that is inherently quadratic in complexity.
Here's another example.
I want to find the intersection of two lists.
And then I want to return a list where
each element appears only once.
So L1 is a list of things, could be numbers,
could be something else.
L2 is similarly a list.
And I'm going to first start by trying
to find a list that has those that appear in both lists.
And then because there might be some duplication
I'm going to clean it up and only return
a list where the elements appear exactly once.
I'm not going to step through the code in detail.
But notice, again, a nice, common pattern.
There is a nested pair of loops.
And what I'm doing here makes sense.
I set up a temporary variable called tmp for temp.
For each element of loop 1 I run through all the elements
of loop 2 asking is that element from loop 1-- from list 1,
rather, in list 2.
And if it is, I add it into temp.
I just appended it to the end of that.
Once I've done all of that, I'm going to clean it up
by sending a new temporary variable called Res result.
And then running through the things that
appear in both lists, I simply say if I haven't already put it
into the result, add it in.
But I'm not going to duplicate it
if it appears more than once.
And then I'm going to return the result res down here.
Key characteristic.
I've got a bottom loop.
It's just a loop.
I've got a nested pair of loops here.
And we've already seen in our earlier example,
that's probably an indication of the quadratic performance.
So let's look at it.
There's my coat and here's what I know.
That first nested loop, by exactly the same analysis
I did with the early example, is going
to take the length of L1 times the length of L2 steps.
Because for every element of L1 I do however many elements
there are in L2 number of steps.
And here, there's no breaking out of it earlier.
So it's literally going to be I do length of L2
steps for every element in L1.
So therefore, the product of those two links.
The second loop, the bottom, just
goes through at most length of L1 number of steps.
If every element of L1 also appeared in L2.
Ah, so now I've got a case of two different orders of growth.
The first one is quadratic.
The second one is linear.
That second term, as we make the problem size really large,
simply gets overwhelmed by the first term.
And so we ignore that second term.
And we simply say this is quadratic in that product
of length of L1 and length of L2.
And again, worst case is in essence
when consider both of the same length we'd
say this is order n squared-- so a nice example
of a quadratic complexity algorithm--
characteristic, nested loops.
Now, that can happen in a wide range of cases.
Here's simply another example where now I'm
simply doing something that's going over a range.
And the only difference here is that that range
may get generated incrementally as I need it.
But otherwise, this is exactly like the two cases
I saw before.
What do I want to look at here?
I want to look at what's the cost of the first loop, which
is I want to do it n times because of that range.
And then what's the cost of the second loop?
I'm also going to do it n times because of that range.
So it's n times n.
Again, it's order n squared.
You see the characteristics of quadratic complexity
algorithms.