...
Just a step back for a second.
We're trying to let you see characteristics
that associate an algorithm with a particular class.
Constant, linear, we just saw a quadratic,
which were things like nested loops that lead to that.
The next class in that hierarchy are exponential complexity
algorithms.
These are the most expensive algorithms.
And of course, the goal is always,
if I can find a solution to a problem that's
lower down in the class of complexities,
I want to do that.
But sometimes, unfortunately, we're
going to be stuck with an exponential algorithm.
And indeed, many important problems
are inherently exponential.
There is no more efficient solution than something
that is exponential.
And that, by the way, is why often when we realize that,
we're going to look for approximate solutions
because we may be able to get a good guess more
quickly than finding the most accurate guess.
A common characteristic to an exponential class algorithm
is a recursive function, that is a function that
calls itself, but in each call calls up more than once.
You saw an example of that, which was Towers of Hanoi.
I remind you, in Towers of Hanoi we
said to move a tower of size n.
We move a tower of size n minus 1 to a spare peg,
do something, and then move that tower back.
So at each reduction of the problem
there were two recursive calls.
And that's characteristic of something that's
exponential class complexity.
Let's look at an example.
And here is actually a wonderful piece of code.
It's very crisp and computes something really interesting
very efficiently, or rather, does it
in a very efficient set of code.
The cost is going to be exponential.
And the idea is if I've got a list, say, of numbers--
could be the integers 1, 2, 3, and 4.
I'd like to generate a list of all the subsets of that list.
So what does that mean?
The empty list will be a subset.
The list of 1 would be a subset.
In fact, every list of 1, of 2, or 3, of 4 would be a subset.
Lists of 1, 2, 1, 3, 1, 4, 2, 3, 2, 4, you get the idea.
So this is going to generate a list
of all of the subsets of the initial list.
Let's look quickly at the code and then more importantly
see what the cost is to compute this.
So the idea is I set up, as always, a little variable here
called Res for result I'm going to return.
And then my base case here is if there is nothing in the list,
the only subset is the empty list.
And I actually return a list of the empty list
because I remind you, I want to return
a list of all possible subsets.
And the only possible subset here is in fact the empty list.
The clever solution, much as we saw with Towers of Hanoi
is to say if I want to generate all
of the subsets of a list, what I can do
is first generate all the subsets with everything
but the last element included.
And I do that in a very elegant way.
I get the list with everything but the last element
and I recursively call this function
that will give me back a list of all
of the subsets of everything but the last element.
I then set into extra a list with just the last element.
And now I create another list.
And for everything in that smaller set-- that
is all of the solutions without the last element--
I also create a solution that includes that last element
as part of each one of those earlier elements.
It's wonderfully clever.
I find a solution to the smaller problem.
And then I say for every case where
I've got a solution, a subset that
doesn't have the last element, I will also I
have a version of it with the last element.
And I do that by simply running through this loop
and adding small, which is the solution
without the last element, tagging the last element
onto it, and putting it into that new list, which is new.
And then finally, I just returned every solution
without the last element and every solution
with the last element.
It's a wonderful piece of recursive coding.
And I don't know what they have here.
About seven lines, I've come up with a great solution to it.
Having said all of that, now I just
want to look at the complexity.
Why is this exponential in size?
And let's look at that.
So there's my coat.
I'm going to make an assumption-- it's actually
a very reasonable assumption-- that I
can do the append operation in constant time.
And that's simply me says I need to know
where the end of the list is without having
to walk down the list.
And that, in fact, happens in Python.
So what does the analysis now say?
It says that the time that I need
is going to include the time to solve the smaller
problem plus the time I need to make
a copy of all of the elements in the smaller problem.
So it's going to be the time I need
here plus making the copyright down here
of all of the elements in the smaller problem.
OK.
So what does that look like?
Well, it's important to think about
what's the size of the smaller problem?
And there I can do a nice piece of analysis.
Because I know that in order to solve this for a set of size K,
there are 2 to the K possible cases.
How do I get that?
Well, if I've got K element-- say
they're integers-- for each integer
I can decide is this one in or not?
So for every integer I got a choice of two.
I've got k of them.
So there are 2 to the k possible cases
that could be generated as I solve the smaller problem.
Now, what does that say?
It says to solve this case, if I've
got n elements in my largest set,
I need to solve a problem of size 2
to the n minus 1, all the subsets
with n minus 1 elements.
I need to solve the problem with 2
to the n minus 2, a problem with 2 to the n minus c, all the way
down to 2 to the 0 or 1 case.
And from mathematics, we know that that
is, in fact, 2 to the n.
And therefore, this is a problem that is exponential.
The base is 2.
But it grows as 2 to the n.
And if you're a little confused about how bad
is it to compare n squared to 2 to the n, try some examples.
You'll see that the exponential one grows much more rapidly
than the quadratic one.
And the characteristic here is I'm
breaking this down into sub problems
that I have to call multiple times,
just as we saw in the Towers of Hanoi case.
So there's a nice characteristic of an exponential complexity
algorithm.
That now has let us have a run through the things we've seen.
And I'll simply remind you very quickly.
Constantine is just doing a set of operations.
There could be a recursive call in there.
But it's going to be constant no matter what
the size of the problem is.
Logarithmic, I'm breaking the problem in half or in portions
as quickly as I can.
And we want to use that idea when we think about things
like bisection search.
Linear, we've already seen it could
be just a loop that I'm doing throughout some number
of times, the number of times being
a reflection of the size of the problem,
or something that recursively calls itself
as in factorial, again, a number of times based
on the size of the problem.
Polynomial, again, we've already seen
examples of that, recursive calls being
very clear examples.
And exponential, characterized by having recursive
calls, but we're breaking the problem
down into multiple calls each time around.
And as I said, with polynomial, the most common one
here is where c is equal to 2.
And a greater characteristic of that is nested loops.