...
So we looked at adding labels, adding titles to our graphs.
Good thing to do if we want to save them,
we want to put them in a paper, we want to hang on to them,
look at them later on.
But we started this discussion by saying we also
wanted to use the plotting or graphing
as a way of thinking about different kinds of results.
We started that when we began plotting different functions
in different windows.
But even there, what I showed you earlier
could have been a bit misleading because it looked
like the linear graph and the exponential graph
grew at different levels.
But we didn't have a clear sense of that
because we didn't change the scales.
The scale on the y-axis for the linear graph
only went up to 30.
The scale on the y-axis for the exponential graph
went up 140,000.
And we'd like to be able to better visualize differences.
So if the scales are different on the graphs,
how could we deal with that?
One option is to explicitly set limits on the axis.
Right now, we're just letting PiLab do that automatically.
It figures out what's the maximum range of y-values,
and it sets the axis scale appropriately.
We could control it.
A second option is to actually plot multiple functions
on the same display, but to choose
which ones I want to display.
We did this earlier when we put all four together
and we saw that that wasn't really effective
because the smallest ones were too small.
But we're going to look at how we
might do a different way of doing that multiple display
to get a better sense of that kind of difference in scale.
So let's look at both of these.
Changing limits on the axes.
Here's the code, things we've been using as before.
Notice again, I'm going to get into that habit of just
clearing the frame before I deal with it.
And now, I can explicitly say, I want
to have the y limit go from 0 to 1000.
I'm picking that number because I
happen to know what this display is going to look like.
Some experimentation might let you decide an appropriate set.
But what you should see here is that when I am plotting,
I have the ability to explicitly set the range on the y-axis.
By the way, I could set the same thing on the x-axis.
And I don't have to show all of the values of the y
function or the x function, I could actually
pull out just a subset of it.
So in this case, I'm going to do a plot for the linear.
I'm going to do a plot for the quadratic, each
in their own frame.
But I'm going to set the y limit to be the same in both frames.
And then I label them.
And let's look at what happens when we do that.
This is actually quite nice.
Why is it nice?
Because now I can see what's the difference
between a linear function and a quadratic function.
We knew that the quadratic would grow more rapidly.
But now we get a sense of that difference,
because I've set it up so that both y-axes have
the same range.
Notice also, I picked a value that has a little bit of a gap
up here.
I happen to know that the y-values are
going to go up to about 800.
I could have lowered it down, but this
was a nice way of picking a range that was going
to let me see that difference.
From the perspective of visualizing data,
this is nice because now I can really
compare how quickly does quadratic
grow relative to linear while still seeing the difference.
What else might I do?
Well I can overlay the plots on top of one another,
but do it in a way where I actually pick which
ones I want to think about.
We saw earlier that trying to compare linear
against exponential is going to be a wash because you'll never
see the linear.
But now, I can go back to the idea of set
up a function or a frame, clear it.
And then in this case, let's plot two functions inside
of that frame, pick a second one,
clear it, and plot another two functions inside of that frame.
And if I do that, again, because I
am calling both of those plots inside of the same figure
they're going to overlay.
And because I'm calling the second pair
of plots inside the same frame, they're
going to get an overlay.
But I have a better way of doing the comparison.
And when I do that, I get the following display.
Now I can see the difference between linear and quadratic,
and I can see the difference between cubic and exponential.
And interestingly, you may not have
realized that cubic, early on, actually
grows a little bit faster than exponential.
But after some point, exponential
takes off and really overwhelms it.
Notice at the same time, I should
be careful about comparing these two graphs
because this one only goes up to 900,
that one goes up to 140,000.
Part of the message for you here--
if I want to compare things, I need
to think about what I'm comparing.
But it gives me a way of actually doing
that visualization in a very nice way.
So there are some times when I want to overlay things
on the same window, and other times
when I want to just have them displayed side by side.
I can do a couple of other things here.
Now that I'm starting to do other displays on top
of things, I could also add a legend
that helps me tell which plot is which.
If I go back to this window, you kind of know
which one's quadratic, which one's linear,
but I'd be handy to label them.
And I can do that.
And in particular, I can add in a label for a plot.
Here, I'm using the keyword label, and then
the equal sign, and then the specific label
to put on each one of them.
And I'm putting obvious labels here.
I'm going to label each one of these plots
so that now when I display them, I'm going
to get a nice display out.
One more thing before I do them.
I need to decide where am I going to put the legend.
And I could actually give it a location
by giving, under the plot function legend,
the keyword loc for location of upper left.
Or I could simply say, put the legend up,
but give it no argument and let PiLab decide what it thinks
is the best location to use.
Notice, by the way, that I need to do this because it's not
just that I put the label here.
I actually have to command PiLab to put a legend in for it
to appear.
OK, with that in mind, what does it look like?
Oh, kind of cool.
Remember I said use the upper left location.
There's the legend.
And now, each graph has a legend associated with it.
So I know that the blue line-- this one down here-- is linear,
and the green line is quadratic.
When I let PiLab decide where to place it,
it makes the decision that it thinks
is the best location to put it.
You might argue that in this case,
putting it in the upper right corner really
isn't great because it overlaps a little bit of the graph.
It might have been better to put it over there.
But we leave it up to PiLab to decide where to place it.
And again, now I know that this is the cubic,
and that is the exponential because the legend tells me
that right there.
So that's great.
I can start adding more information to the plots
that I'm using.